<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-15T19:53:16-05:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Amanda Lynn Elliott</title><subtitle>thoughts like these rack my brain and keep me sane
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Artistic Journey</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artistic Journey" /><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/art-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/art/"><![CDATA[<p>Finding my way back to art after deciding not to do art as a career has been interesting. Even if trying to do art full-time depresses me, I still have an inherent need to create. I feel much better when I regularly take the time to express myself visually.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/2021_01-18-ColorStudy4_StaticElec2.PNG" alt="static electricity digital painting" /></p>

<blockquote>If I could say it in words there would be no reason to paint.<footer>— Edward Hopper</footer></blockquote>

<p>After completing undergrad in Florida, I had the task of moving to upstate New York for grad school. This entailed going through the many art pieces, sketchbooks, and journals that I had made throughout the years. This process elicited emotions ranging from confusion (so much of what I wrote/drew was nonsensical) and disgust (or borderline disturbing) to inspiring. It’s a strange feeling to inspire yourself from the past.</p>

<p>Focusing on the pieces that uplifted me instead of making me cringe, I have collected them onto an <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/art/">Art page</a> and will describe my artistic journey here.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="editorial-illustration-and-education">Editorial Illustration and Education</h3>

<p>After high school, I became inspired by editorial illustrators like Victo Ngai and Emiliano Ponzi. I fell in love with editorial illustration as a craft: art that can be eye-catching, but also a glimpse into the themes of the article that the illustrator was commissioned to advertise for. I loved the way that they combined symbols in unexpected ways.</p>

<p>Around this time, there was a heat wave in the UK that was leading to deaths, because the buildings were not equipped with air conditioning and generally not designed for such high temperatures. This event had the potential illustration elements of heat and buildings, which could be combined in a novel way: Big Ben melting. In a world of increasing temperatures, the reliability of our infrastructure is failing, as if it is becoming lava beneath our feet.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/illo-Big-Ben.jpg" alt="Big Ben melting illustration" /></p>

<p>Most of my art pieces at this time focused around education. These pieces were inspired by my frustration with the lack of self-awareness I had at the time and blaming the lack of autonomy provided to students by the public school system. I felt that the emphasis on standardized testing was a hinderance to self-discovery of students and the creativity of teachers’ lesson plans. It was a mundane process of memorize, regurgitate, and repeat.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/education.png" alt="education illustration" /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/20230603_172113_fix.jpg" alt="moebius strip standardized testing" /></p>

<p>This was the time period when I made this fun piece as well, which suggests diverging into a creative and whimsical journey.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/paper-journey.jpg" alt="notebook paper journey illustration" /></p>

<h3 id="dreams">Dreams</h3>

<p>When I was 14 years old, I started keeping a dream journal. If you decide to keep a dream journal, you have to commit to writing your dreams in the first moments when you open your eyes. Dreams are time-sensitive. The second you wake up, they start slipping away. In the haze inbetween waking-and-sleeping, your handwriting or phone-typing dexterity may be terrible, but making the effort to record them can be valuable.</p>

<p>What I learned by studying the work of editorial illustrators was how to combine elements and symbols in unexpected ways. We are naturally better at this in our dreams. We easily make unexpected connections in our dreams, which is why hearing somebody else describe their dream sounds scattered, even if it makes perfect sense to them.</p>

<p>After recording a dream (and snoozing for a while longer), the record you keep can become inspiration for later drawings.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/37019_4849274757961_1411328728_n.jpg" alt="dream sketch - cards" /></p>

<p>Dreams are a playground where your subconscious mind enacts scenarios. It allows you to face the things you are afraid to (nightmares) or achieve the things you desire. Or if you engage in some playful visualization while falling asleep, your dreams can become wildly untethered from your walking reality. You can end up dreaming that you are not yourself, but other people, in other ages.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/263038_4849271797887_911940506_n.jpg" alt="dream sketch - monster" /></p>

<p>It can be enlightening to analyze the dreams that are especially emotionally intense. The questions I sometimes ask myself are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>How did I feel during the dream? What in my waking life might be making me feel like that?</li>
  <li>What are the main elements in the dream? Characters, animals, monsters, or the landscape itself? How do these elements make me feel? Do they represent anything from my waking life?</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/20230603_161624_fix.jpg" alt="dream sketch - falling in the forest" /></p>

<h3 id="creative-process">Creative Process</h3>

<p>Recently, I have gotten into painting, and have developed a creative process that I find rewarding.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/2021_01-23-Jennifer-crop.PNG" alt="portrait painting" /></p>

<p>Before changing careers, my creative process would have been “Wake up. Make something beautiful and interesting. Sleep. Repeat.” The only problem was that it wasn’t inspired action. The outcome when I force an art piece, even if it is <em>technically</em> good, is something that people don’t resonate with, and that makes even me sad to look at. Why force ourselves to do anything? Forcing yourself to make art is like an oxymoron.</p>

<p>If you ever go to art fairs, you may notice that some artist’s booths have difficulty attacting people, while others are overflowing with people buying art pieces. The difference is not typically skill, either, but the artist’s vibe. Some artists feel desperate, “<em>Please look at my art. Please buy something. Please stop making me feel like a failure</em>,” while others are uplifting, “<em>Look at what I have made. I hope it uplifts and inspires you.</em>”. This difference is profound. Speaking from experience, it took a lot of failed pieces for me to realize that creating for the sake of getting something out of it, such as validation, is a lost cause.</p>

<p>When you embark to express yourself creatively, make sure it is from not a place of lack or neediness, but a positive desire to share a part of yourself.</p>

<figure id="veil">
<img class="gallery-veil" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/veil/1.jpg" />
<figcaption>
When walking around Mt. Hope Cemetery in Rochester, NY, I kept seeing statues of urns that were half-covered with cloth. Apparently, this is a <a href="https://historyinstone.blogspot.com/2012/12/the-draped-urn.html">popular symbol that was used for statues in the 1800s</a>, used to symbolize the deceased passing through the veil between life and death.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Lately my creative process has the following steps:</p>

<h4 id="1-explore">1. Explore</h4>

<p>It is nice to regularly get exposed to different kinds of creative media, be it sci-fi novels, movies, plays, museums, video games, or nature itself. When I do these activities, I regularly take pictures to later use as reference images for art pieces. Occasionally scrolling through websites like Pinterest can also provide inspiration.</p>

<h4 id="2-create-space">2. Create Space</h4>

<p>It is difficult to create if you feel crowded or overwhelmed by clutter. For me, this step means cleaning my desk. It is important to free up the space needed in order to create something new. This space can be physical, but also mental by meditating or sitting quietly with calming music.</p>

<h4 id="3-invoke-what-you-want-to-create">3. Invoke what you want to create</h4>

<p>Define what you desire. What feeling or concept do you want to express? How would it feel to have accomplished sharing this with others?</p>

<p>This part is like sending an invitation in the mail, and then waiting for the RSVP.</p>

<h4 id="4-wait">4. Wait</h4>

<p>Once you have defined what you desire to create, you can now take a step back. From anywhere to a few seconds, or longer time periods, like days or weeks, during which your mind will be working on your idea in the background. At some point you will then get struck with inspiration to create it.</p>

<p>It is like when you are speaking to somebody and they lose their train of thought. Inevitably, the second they give up trying to think of the thought and start taking about something else, it comes back to them. Stepping away allows you to detach from the outcome, and gives time for serendipitous events to occur that may enrich your work.</p>

<h4 id="5-ride-the-wave-of-inspiration">5. Ride the wave of inspiration</h4>

<p>When the impulse to create the desired idea strikes, it’s important to act on it. I find that if I delay and try to come back to create it much later, I usually can’t summon the same level of inspiration that I had before. It feels like surfing. You see a wave come that you want to ride, and if you miss it, you need to wait for the next wave rather than chase after the one you missed. We are constantly growing and changing everyday. The concepts that you find the most compelling today may be different than tomorrow, and that’s okay. Whenever I miss the wave, I simply go back to Step 3.</p>

<h4 id="6-limit-the-options">6. Limit the options</h4>

<p>When riding the wave it’s important to prevent overwhelm, frustration, or in general negative emotions that can derail the process. To do this, I tend to think about separating technique from expression. If there is a new medium that I want to try out, I usually work out the kinks with that by doing some studies. That way when I want to create something that has more emotion to it, I feel more confident. I become less preoccupied with the left-side of my brain, making and analyzing mistakes and correcting them, instead allowing the right-side of my brain to utilize the technique as easily as riding a bike. The medium them becomes an extension of yourself that you don’t have to think about how to use.</p>

<p>Achieving a flow state is a balancing act between boredom and anxiety. If you are bored with the media or techniques that you usually use, it could be a sign to try to mix it up. But a complete overhaul can be overwhelming.</p>

<p>Either way, I like to keep the process simple. When I started digital painting in high school, I installed hundreds of specialized Photoshop brushes which led to analysis paralysis. Now I use the simplier software called Krita and limit myself to just two paintbrushes. I maintain that same philosophy when I paint with goauche. You can accomplish a lot with a limited toolset. If a tool feels like it’s weighing you down, let it go.</p>

<p>You can come up with different limitations, such as only using two colors, or limiting a sketch to the small real-estate provided by a post-it note.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/pangolin.jpg" alt="pangolin drinking tea sketch" /></p>

<h4 id="7-feel-into-it">7. Feel into it</h4>

<p>Art is a visual illusion that is only convincing if you believe it while making it. What feeling are you trying to trasmit? Follow that feeling to the end.</p>

<p>Once you have established a desire to express a certain feeling/idea/concept, and that wave of inspiration comes, there is a relief that follows finishing that work. One of my favorite movie scenes is of music composer Robert Frobisher from Cloud Atlas. He is down on his luck, running out of money and starving, but he obsessively perseveres to complete his magnum opus, the Cloud Atlas Sextet.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/Cloud Atlas/Frobisher1.jpg" alt="Robert Frobisher from Cloud Atlas, composing music" /></p>
<blockquote>The end rushes towards me. Unable to eat, or sleep. Like Ewing, the mortal coil has become a noose. Would rather become music.<footer>— Robert Frobisher, <i>Cloud Atlas</i></footer></blockquote>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/Cloud Atlas/Frobisher2.jpg" alt="sheet music" /> 
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/Cloud Atlas/Frobisher3.jpg" alt="Frobisher finishes the Cloud Atlas Sextet" /></p>

<p>“It’s done,” he says, drawing the bold double bar line to complete his composition.</p>

<p>Frobisher is exhausted and relieved, but also changed. The act of creating is a transformative process, leaving you different than when you started. It is this regenerative process that I love about viewing and making art.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/art-journey/fox transformation.jpeg" alt="fox and man transformation sketch" /></p>

<p>It has taken many trials and errors to find a rewarding creative process that is uplifting for myself, and for those who I show my art to. I hope that my perspective inspires you to find your unique way of embarking on an artistic journey of your own. To see my other art pieces, you can vist my <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/art/">Art page</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="art" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="painting" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="inspiration" /><category term="dreams" /><category term="illustration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Finding my way back to art after deciding not to do art as a career has been interesting. Even if trying to do art full-time depresses me, I still have an inherent need to create. I feel much better when I regularly take the time to express myself visually. If I could say it in words there would be no reason to paint.— Edward Hopper After completing undergrad in Florida, I had the task of moving to upstate New York for grad school. This entailed going through the many art pieces, sketchbooks, and journals that I had made throughout the years. This process elicited emotions ranging from confusion (so much of what I wrote/drew was nonsensical) and disgust (or borderline disturbing) to inspiring. It’s a strange feeling to inspire yourself from the past. Focusing on the pieces that uplifted me instead of making me cringe, I have collected them onto an Art page and will describe my artistic journey here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Undergrad Research Projects</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/undergrad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Undergrad Research Projects" /><published>2024-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/undergrad-complete</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2024/01/undergrad/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a wild journey since I wrote about my experience of deciding to <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/07/finding-purpose/">switch from art to a physics career</a>, and since recapping on my <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/01/first-semester/">first semester</a> of undergrad in 2020. Undergrad was very busy. It felt like I had just started to get into the swing of things, but then we were hit with the Coronavirus pandemic, and my university joined the vast majority in the country to switch to completely remote learning for a semester, then to hybrid, and then back to in-person.</p>

<p>Once I decided that physics was the path for me, the implication of that meant getting a PhD. The process of applying and getting accepted into a graduate physics program was demanding, but rewarding.</p>

<p>During the pandemic, I took advantage of the remote learning to take an electrical engineering internship. I worked on projects for the Department of Defense, and then got a summer internship in Colorado to work on a physics research project for CERN. Later, during senior year, I did a plasma simulation project to investigate the mysterious weather phenomenon, ball lightning.</p>

<p>It was a very productive four years. After graduating, I moved from Florida to upstate New York for graduate school at Univeristy of Rochester. Currently being on winter break in-between semesters feels like the perfect time to recap on my undergrad research projects here.</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="department-of-defense-projects">Department of Defense Projects</h3>

<p>Sophmore year, I did a rewarding year-long electrical engineering internship at <a href="https://mainstream-engr.com/">Mainstream Engineering</a>. Working there allowed me to use electronics to do research for the Department of Defense while collaborating with engineers from a variety of fields, such as electrical, mechanical, and chemical.</p>

<p>I worked on two projects while I was there. Since these projects are ITAR restricted, I can’t describe them in detail, but can provide overviews.</p>

<p>The first project was funded by the Air Force. The goal of this project is to create a device that monitors a constant speed drive on A-10 aircrafts. The developed device reads a voltage pulse from a variable reluctance sensor and logs data for each flight.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/A-10.webp" alt="Airforce A-10 Warthog Aircraft" />
<figcaption>Source: <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/37233/the-a-10-warthog-is-preparing-for-its-biggest-upgrade-in-over-a-decade">The War Zone</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The hardware and software that I worked on was tested successfully by the Air Force, in following with the testing plan that I developed.</p>

<p>One of my favorite parts of this project was reverse engineering a variable reluctance sensor, which included using a scanning electron microscope to identify unknown metals using energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy and running tests on my prototypes. Building and testing this prototypes was also fun, and involved 3D printing, winding solenoids, and sizing various magnets.</p>

<p>The second project I worked on was a novel liquid nitrogen generation system. The system takes surrounding air through an air compressor, and through a series of devices (cryocooler, vapor compression system, etc.), generates liquid nitrogen. For this project, I programmed a touchscreen logic controller for operating the devices via relays, analog signals, and serial communications. The system was monitored by routinely reading a variety of sensors for temperature, pressure, and mass flow. I also programmed data transmission from the controller to a computer for analyzing how the system operates over long periods of time in order improve its efficiency.</p>

<p>It was a wonderful experience learning how to collaborate on projects, solder, troubleshoot, program hardware, and write documentation.</p>

<h3 id="space-scientists-and-particle-physicists">Space Scientists and Particle Physicists</h3>

<p>Then summer of junior year, I was accepted at a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at University of Colorado, Boulder. This meant packing my bags to live in Boulder for 10 weeks.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/Boulder.jpg" alt="UC Boulder campus view from physics building" /></p>

<p>The Boulder campus is beautiful. From my dorm, my commute to the lab I worked in consisted of a 10 minute bike ride along a scenic trail along a spring.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/Boulder-trail.jpg" alt="Boulder bike trail" /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/Boulder2.jpg" alt="Boulder deer" /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/Boulder3.jpg" alt="Boulder deer outside of dorm" /></p>

<p>My summer research at UC Boulder was supported by the National Science Foundation. It was the result of an interesting collaboration. Space scientists in Boulder and particle physicists in Switzerland started working together when researchers at the European Council for Nuclear Research (<a href="https://home.cern/">CERN</a>) reached out to the Institute for Modeling Plasma, Atmospheres, and Cosmic Dust (<a href="https://impact.colorado.edu/about.html">IMPACT</a>) to test a theory. They suspected that the Large Hadron Collider was experiencing shutdowns due to electrostatic dust lofting. The synchrotron radiation generated when accelerated proton bunches travel through the collider could charge the dust inside it. The electric field generated between these protons and the grounded chamber walls could generate a force to pull these charged dust grains from the walls. This project involved running experiments in vacuum chambers and developing a script to extract data from recorded high-speed footage of these experiments.</p>

<p>The experiment setup shown below consisted of a high-speed camera positioned looking into a vacuum chamber. Inside the vacuum chamber was a grounded plate where dust would be deposited. About a centimeter above this is a metallic mesh that could have a potential difference of up to 3 kiloVolts between it and the grounded plate. Above the dust setup was a tungsten filament, that when a sufficient current was passed through it and heating voltage was across it, would send a beam of electrons down to the dust. We were interested in studying these two types of electrostatic dust lofting: (1) lofting due to charging via this electron beam, and (2) lofting due to high voltage when the beam was turned off and up to 3 kV was placed across the metallic mesh.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/exp-setup.png" alt="electrostatic dust lofting experiment setup diagram" /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/chamber-setup.png" alt="photo of experiment setup" /></p>

<p>Setting up the experiment involved learning how to work with vacuum chambers, and applying some of the skills I learned from a week-long machine shop training that UC Boulder provided. During the program, I learned how to work metal by sawing, drilling, tapping, and also how to use the lathe and mill.</p>

<p>We also ran some plasma diagnostics on the chamber using an emissive probe (pictured below) and a Langmuir probe.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/chamber.jpg" alt="chamber with diagnostic probe" /></p>

<p>Alongside the data collection of setting up the experiment and varying our parameters of interest, I also developed a particle tracking script to process the resulting high-speed footage. The goal of this script was to detect lofted particles and calculate their upward velocity and acceleration. From this the electric charge on the dust grain could be calculated. By comparing the change of brightness in-between consecutive video frames, the script was able to detect movement. One of my first test results from the script is below.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/tracking-script-first-test.gif" alt="particle tracking script - initial test results" /></p>

<p>Surprisingly, with the introduction of a tunable script parameter, it could detect multiple lofted particles at the same time, while also ignoring background noise. Unfortunately, it was still sensitive to brightness differences between videos, and so each video had to be processed individually rather than running them in batches.</p>

<p>I also developed a way to calculate the size of lofted particles using what’s called a flood fill algorithm. If you have ever used the paintbucket tool on drawing software like Paint MS, then you have used a flood fill algorithm before. When you click a pixel with the paintbucket tool, it takes all the surrounding region that has that same color and changes it to a new color. I used and modified this algorithm to select for a <em>range of brightness values</em> instead of color to identify the lofted dust particle and calculate its diameter (usually 10-50 micrometers). A result of this is below, with the result of the flood fill colored yellow.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/flood-fill.png" alt="script - flood fill algorithm" /></p>

<p>One of the differences between our two types of electrostatic dust lofting was the type of trajectory the dust grain traveled in. For the high voltage lofting, a strong vertical electric field was applied which caused the dust to travel vertically upward. However, for lofting due to charging, the charge build-up between dust grains would repel eachother, causing parabolic trajectories. For this type of lofting, I further developed the script to calculate the lofting angle.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/charging-script.gif" alt="script - lofting angle calculation" /></p>

<p>These particle tracking scripts are available on <a href="https://github.com/amandalynnelliott/particle_tracking">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>Our results were promising to indicate that the Large Hadron Collider was experiencing shutdowns due to electrostatic dust lofting. The goal of the project was then to characterize the paramaters that facilitate or inhibit dust lofting, with the long-term goal of dust mitigation at the collider. Throughout the project, I had the invaluable guidance from my advisors in Boulder, along with the insight provided by four CERN collaborators. It was an unsuspecting collaboration between space scientists and particle physicists.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/Boulder/Boulder-group-photo.jpg" alt="UC Boulder REU summer 2022 group photo" />
<figcaption>
UC Boulder 2022 summer REU program group photo.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>At the culmination of my contribution to this research, I presented at Florida Tech’s Northrop Grumman Senior Showcase 2023 and won the awards for Best in Physics and Space Sciences, and Best in Science. We also presented a poster at the <a href="https://www.ipac23.org/">International Particle Accelerator Conference</a> 2023 in Venice, Italy.</p>

<h3 id="ball-lightning-and-plasma-physics">Ball Lightning and Plasma Physics</h3>

<p>During my senior year, I decided to indulge one of my more fringe research interests.</p>

<p>The realization that led to me switching my career from art to physics is that I am happiest when I focus on solving puzzles. The most interesting puzzle that I am working on is one that I have experienced firsthand. What I am about to describe is strange, but I ask that you have an open mind. The things that we consider strange are just things that are yet to be scientifically explained.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/Pop-Guide_lightning-photo_cropped.png" />
<figcaption>Source: H. Boerner. Ball Lightning: A Popular Guide to a Longstanding Mystery in Atmospheric Electricity. Springer, 2019.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>One night when I was twelve, I was trying to fall asleep, but I noticed light that kept filling my room from my window. It was almost like cars were passing by, but the street I lived on was not a busy one, and so I found it odd.</p>

<p>I looked out the window, and saw over the woods in the lot across the street, an orb of white light moving horizontally in the sky. My eyes widened, and I thought, “What is that?” Just then it descended from the sky and came towards me. It was an orb of white light, the size of a soccer ball. It hovered outside my bedroom window a few feet off the ground. It moved horizontally. It would go down the street, outside of my line of sight, and then return. For about an hour it moved in a way that defied any explanation, even going between and around the tree branches of the oak tree in the front yard. It was accompanied by a buzzing or humming noise that made my head feel strange. I tried to drown this out by putting earphones in and listening to music. I spent half of this time hiding under the covers, trying to pretend that it wasn’t there.</p>

<p>I went to school the next day as if nothing had happened, telling myself that, “I was either visited by aliens, or I am crazy.”</p>

<p>I didn’t tell anybody about the experience until junior year of high school. I confided in my friend, and he asked me, “How do you know that it wasn’t a dream?” I said that it felt so real. I could vividly remember the type of MP3 player that I was using to drown out the humming, the one that I would later accidentally break due to water damage when I would forget it in my pocket during a field trip to a lagoon. I told him how I even remembered the song that I was playing over and over again, which was “Everlong” by Foo Fighters.</p>

<p>“Foo Fighters,” he said. “That’s interesting.”</p>

<p>“Why is that,” I responded.</p>

<p>Apparently, Foo Fighters were the name given by World War II pilots to describe the strange orbs of lights that they would see while flying. “Foo,” being French for fire. They called these objects either fireballs or fire fighters.</p>

<p>It wasn’t until high school that I discovered the name for the strange thing I witnessed: a rare weather phenomenon called ball lightning, so named because it tends to be observed during thunderstorms and near lightning strikes. Afterward, I was too scared to share the ordeal with anyone for years for fear of sounding crazy. I was surprised and relieved to learn that thousands of eyewitnesses had reported the same properties I had observed. This event has been a guiding force for my curiosity.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/Richmann.png" />
<figcaption>
Engraving of the ball lightning
caused death of Russian physicist Georg
Wilhelm Richmann in 1753 [Boerner,
2019]
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>My ball lightning experience has inspired and challenged me. It gives me the firsthand knowledge that there are many unsolved mysteries in the world and the conviction to consider unique perspectives when trying to solve them. Whenever I tell this story a wave of apprehension washes over me. Will they believe me, or will they think that I hallucinated? To witness something that should not exist was a challenging experience that changed me. I had two options to process it. Either I could accept that my perception is wrong and that I am crazy or accept that my understanding of reality is wrong. Either way, the discomfort will always be there in the back of my mind until it is resolved. This discomfort is the feeling of an unfinished puzzle.</p>

<p>Senior year of undergrad, I decided to explore this strange phenomena. I started research under advisement of a computational mathematician and a plasma physicist that specializes in solar wind.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/BL_shell_Wu.PNG" />
<figcaption>
H-C. Wu. Relativistic-Microwave Theory of Ball Lightning. Scientific Reports 6, 28263, 2016.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I came across Hui-Chun Wu’s 2016 paper describing a potential theory for the creation of ball lightning at the end of lightning strikes. This theory involved relativistically accelerated electrons at the end of the lightning leader, that could lead to a type of radiation transmission that could ionize the air, forming a kind of stable, standing microwave, trapped by a plasma shell. Supporting the theory that ball lightning objects are hollow on the inside is that the most commonly reported ways that these objects terminate is either (1) violent termination in which the object comes in contact with something sharp, like edge of a table, causing it to explode with a loud burst of energy, or (2) peaceful termination in which it dissipates like a gas. These ways of termination are similar to how everyday soap bubbles tend to either pop or fade away. My goal was to replicate his simulation results and build on top of them.</p>

<p>The first thing I did was set up a plasma simulation software called <a href="https://smileipic.github.io/Smilei/">Smilei</a>, which is an open source particle-in-cell code.</p>

<p>One of the simple tutorials that can be run with the code is a laser incident on a column of plasma. This example is used to demonstrate the radiation pressure, or pondermotive force, that can allow for strong electric fields to induce a force on plasma. This effect depends on the number density (number of particles per volume) of the plasma, in relation to a defined critical number density. When the number density is much larger than the critical density, most of the laser energy is reflected by the plasma. When the number density is much less, the laser passes through the plasma as if it was transparent.</p>

<p>In-between these extremes, you can get the effect of moving plasma with electromagnetic energy via the laser, like below.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/electrons_and_Ex_Bx.gif" alt="laser incident on plasma column" /></p>

<p>In the time that I was working on this project, I was able to replicate the first of Wu’s simulations that involved simulating the type of radiation that could develop at the end of a lightning leader, in the microwave range. I wasn’t able to replicate the second simulation to trap this radiation into a stable circular shape. For my simulation, I was able to get the plasma bubble to form, but it never stabilized.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/New_Ez.gif" />
<figcaption>
Simulation 2 electric field input.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/BL/SHOWCASE_SPRING2023_VIDEO_MATH_BLSIM.gif" />
<figcaption>
Simulation 2 plasma number density result. There is plasma shell formation, but it is not stable.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>There are many physical effects that the simulation does not take into account, such as electron collisions with the air which occur at a rate that is much faster than the simulation time scale. It would also be interesting to consider the effect of vertical forces, such as gravity, and the upward convective force, to explain how ball lightning objects appear to hover at a stable distance from the ground.</p>

<p>What fascinates me about ball lightning, and what may be the key to understanding them, may lie in their stability. What parameters are key to determining the lifespan of these objects, which is usually observed to be seconds to minutes? Could it be an interplay between internal pressure and plasma shell surface tension, similar to that of everyday soap bubbles?</p>

<p>Elegant models and equations provide us with the predictive power to explain a variety of phenomena. The practice of physics requires a balance of approximating reality without oversimplifying it.</p>

<p>This is the challenge of developing theories. What physical effects do you include or exclude? The gravitational effect of Pluto certainly exists, but this is of course negligible. Determining what effects are important can only be accomplished through rigorous observation and experimentation, without which, theories can digress from reality. This is the challenge of ball lightning. It is so rare that it is difficult to obtain data directly from ball lightning objects. Until we understand the conditions under which it is created, we cannot predict where it will be created, or artificially create it. Lightning researchers in China were at the right place at the right time, and able to record the <a href="https://physics.aps.org/articles/v7/5">spectrum of a ball lightning object in 2014</a>. Other than this, information about these objects are limited to statistical analysis of eyewitness reports, which can be unreliable.</p>

<p>Describing the creation, stability, and termination of ball lightning is an outstanding physics problem. My project materials are available <a href="http://www.bukshtynov.xyz/research_undergrad.html">here</a>. I presented this research at Florida Tech’s 2023 Northrop Grumman sponsored Senior Showcase and won Best in Mathematics. I also presented a poster for this research at the Florida Undergraduate Research Conference, St. Thomas University, Miami FL (February 17-18, 2023).</p>

<h3 id="research-process-and-graduate-school">Research Process and Graduate School</h3>

<p>These undergraduate research projects gave me an appreciation for how professional research is done. It is highly collaborative, requires a lot of communication, and it usually takes much longer than you expect to make progress. Research projects are always a work-in-progress, but sharing results is nonetheless encouraged. Almost always, the research digresses in ways that you would never expect. I learned the importance of being flexible with schedules and plans. Encountering unexpected difficulties is not a sign of failure, but comes with the territory of trying to discover new things.</p>

<p>One thing I learned from these experiences is that I enjoy collaborating with people from a wide variety of fields. I find that consulting with people with different areas of expertise is enriching, and saves me time by preventing me from falling into traps.</p>

<p>Diversity and collaboration are necessary to push the boundaries of knowledge. The intersection of fields seems to be the most interesting source of discoveries because the cross-pollination of ideas is facilitated.</p>

<p>During senior year, I also applied to graduate schools. I was so busy that I ended up making most of my conference posters while on plane rides to visit the schools that I was accepted to.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/UtahState.jpg" />
<figcaption>
A cafe by Utah State University
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I was thrilled to accept the offer for the physics PhD program at the University of Rochester.</p>

<h3 id="moving-to-rochester">Moving to Rochester</h3>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/UR_Fall.jpg" />
<figcaption>
University of Rochester Rush Rhees Library
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I am excited to be doing my graduate research at the <a href="https://www.lle.rochester.edu/">Labratory for Laser Energetics</a>. Given last year’s <a href="https://www.llnl.gov/archive/news/lawrence-livermore-national-laboratory-achieves-fusion-ignition">fusion ignition</a> achieved by Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, this is an exciting time to be in laser and plasma physics.</p>

<p>One of the concepts that my research will concentrate on is a powerful way to control lasers called a flying focus:</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2024/01/AElliott_N2Y_Flying-Focus.jpg" />
<figcaption>
Source: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2018-11-focus-lasers-space.html">Phys.org</a>
</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For the first year of my program, I am focusing on coursework and teaching undergraduate physics labs. Though, I am thrilled to continue research this summer.</p>

<p>I am grateful for all of the research opportunities that I have had and continue to contribute to. My hope for my graduate studies and career is to continue working with diverse groups of scientifically minded people to further humanity’s understanding of reality by solving its outstanding puzzles.</p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="announcements" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="undergrad" /><category term="undergraduate" /><category term="physics" /><category term="math" /><category term="science" /><category term="STEM" /><category term="ball" /><category term="lightning" /><category term="research" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a wild journey since I wrote about my experience of deciding to switch from art to a physics career, and since recapping on my first semester of undergrad in 2020. Undergrad was very busy. It felt like I had just started to get into the swing of things, but then we were hit with the Coronavirus pandemic, and my university joined the vast majority in the country to switch to completely remote learning for a semester, then to hybrid, and then back to in-person. Once I decided that physics was the path for me, the implication of that meant getting a PhD. The process of applying and getting accepted into a graduate physics program was demanding, but rewarding. During the pandemic, I took advantage of the remote learning to take an electrical engineering internship. I worked on projects for the Department of Defense, and then got a summer internship in Colorado to work on a physics research project for CERN. Later, during senior year, I did a plasma simulation project to investigate the mysterious weather phenomenon, ball lightning. It was a very productive four years. After graduating, I moved from Florida to upstate New York for graduate school at Univeristy of Rochester. Currently being on winter break in-between semesters feels like the perfect time to recap on my undergrad research projects here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Corona Connection: Rise of the Communities</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/07/corona-connection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corona Connection: Rise of the Communities" /><published>2020-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/07/corona-connection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/07/corona-connection/"><![CDATA[<p>The last few months have highlighted our need for community. Despite the availability of technology and the ability to easily communicate to whomever and whenever we please, we live in an age of loneliness, where many people feel like they have few people (or even no one) that they can rely on for emotional support.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/07/keywest-cactus.JPG" alt="Key West, FL" /></p>

<p>Social distancing has been a catalyst of personal growth for many of us as quarantine forced us into solitude and a period of self-reflection. It was the pause button on the busy-ness of everyday life that was uncomfortable, but needed. Empty grocery store shelves broke the illusion of infinite abundance, and alerted us to the fragility of modern society. After only a month of reduced transportation, city air and waterways got noticeably clearer.</p>

<p>These experiences seem to say, “You are not in this alone.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your actions are inexorably linked to every other person and living thing on the planet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the absence of being able to socialize, I realized how much I took it for granted. I realized all the people I wished I had reached out to and met when I had the chance before my university went online. I also remembered the times in which I was in need of help, desperate for community support but felt so alone.</p>

<p>During quarantine, I was learning about lightning and came across the term “Corona Discharge.” It is a luminous effect when an electric field causes charged particles to radiate from a conductive surface. If the electric field grows strong enough, or if the conductive object is brought close enough, this charge can arc between objects, as shown here.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/07/arc.jpg" alt="corona discharge" />
<figcaption>Source: <a href="http://tsgphysics.mit.edu/front/?page=demo.php&amp;letnum=D%2029">TSG MIT Physics</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The lesson from Corona is clear: <em>If you want community, you have to reach out!</em></p>

<p>Similarly, we need to bridge gaps between perspectives.</p>

<p><em>We are facing many challenges that simply cannot be addressed in isolation.</em> To the contrary, many of our problems arose from isolated thinking—from thinking that the isolated actions of one corporation, or of one person—doesn’t affect others. Now we know better.</p>

<p>The two main issues I will touch on are Black Lives Matter and the environment.<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="black-lives-matter">Black Lives Matter</h3>

<p>The footage and stories that have been circulating from the BLM movement has been nothing short of a wake up call for me. Police brutality is a problem that simply cannot be ignored anymore. The stories that we hear are likely only a fraction of what has happened, and it highlights the need for serious repercussions and accountability to be put in place that would prevent officers from behaving aggressively without cause, putting people in life-threatening holds, giving confusing commands at gunpoint, and falsifying reports.</p>

<p>The article <a href="https://medium.com/@OfcrACab/confessions-of-a-former-bastard-cop-bb14d17bc759">Confessions of a Former Bastard Cop</a> should be required reading. Some eye-opening quotes include:</p>

<p class="sidenote">
"In fact, let me tell you about an extremely formative experience: in my <b>police academy class</b>, we had a clique of around six trainees who routinely bullied and harassed other students: intentionally scuffing another trainee’s shoes to get them in trouble during inspection, sexually harassing female trainees, cracking racist jokes, and so on. Every quarter, we were to write anonymous evaluations of our squadmates. <b>I wrote scathing accounts of their behavior, thinking I was helping keep bad apples out of law enforcement and believing I would be protected.</b> Instead, the academy staff read my complaints to them out loud and outed me to them and never punished them, causing me to get harassed for the rest of my academy class. That’s how I learned that even police leadership hates rats. <b>That’s why no one is 'changing things from the inside.' They can’t, the structure won’t allow it."</b><br /><br />

"Understand: Police officers are part of the state monopoly on violence and all police training reinforces this monopoly as a cornerstone of police work, a source of honor and pride. Many cops fantasize about getting to kill someone in the line of duty, egged on by others that have. One of my training officers told me about the time he shot and killed a mentally ill homeless man wielding a big stick. He bragged that he 'slept like a baby' that night. <b>Official training teaches you how to be violent effectively and when you’re legally allowed to deploy that violence, but 'unofficial training' teaches you to desire violence</b>, to expand the breadth of your violence without getting caught, and to erode your own compassion for desperate people so you can justify punitive violence against them."<br /><br />

- Officer A. Cab, <a href="https://medium.com/@OfcrACab/confessions-of-a-former-bastard-cop-bb14d17bc759">Confessions of a Former Bastard Cop</a>
</p>

<p>The article points out an important question: <em>Why are cops the first people we call for problems that would be better addressed by social workers?</em> When the use of lethal force is so rarely needed, and when cops predominantly get to the scene after the crime has already been committed, why is the primary tool for people in crisis an armed soldier, whose primary tool is a gun?</p>

<p>Why are so many resources being used to fight crime, when <em>preventing</em> crime could be magnitudes of order more effective?</p>

<figure>
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/dataisbeautiful/comments/hflutt/reimagining_the_los_angeles_city_budget_oc/?utm_medium=android_app&amp;utm_source=share"><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/07/fund-the-community2.gif" alt="Reimagining the Los Angeles city budget by sandusky_hohoho" /></a>
<figcaption>Reimagining the Los Angeles city budget by <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/dataisbeautiful/comments/hflutt/reimagining_the_los_angeles_city_budget_oc/?utm_medium=android_app&amp;utm_source=share">sandusky_hohoho</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The challenge that the BLM movement faces is that it has periods where it makes a lot of noise, but then fades away. The movement needs more calls-to-action. Besides protesting and signing petitions, what action steps can be taken? What specific changes can be implemented?</p>

<p><em>This movement is no substitute for strong communities.</em> It can be a source of inspiration, but at a certain point, the baton needs to be passed to local community members, and not dropped. This can come in the form of shared conversations, local events, and the kind of sustained actions that lead to changes in local representation, policies, and culture.</p>

<p>When it comes to social concerns, there is a wide discrepancy in commitment: People either devote themselves wholly to a cause, start a nonprofit, and vow to “change the world,” or like most of us, are far too busy with working full-time to take any action at all.</p>

<p><em>Your actions are inexorably linked to every other person and living thing on the planet.</em></p>

<p>Another lesson from Corona is that we can be productive, often from working at home, and by working less hours. A lot of the stress we feel in everyday life is artificial and unnecessary, and we are much more efficient and capable than we give ourselves credit for. In accepting this, we can liberate some of our energy and time from meeting our survival needs for the purpose of building and serving our communities.</p>

<p>Actions don’t have to be large in order to make an impact.</p>

<h3 id="environment">Environment</h3>

<p><em>What’s good for the environment and what’s good for the economy are often two different things. How can we make them the same thing?</em></p>

<p>It simply does not pay to be a company that cares about the environment. If anything, companies are rewarded with greater profits for doing exactly the opposite: being negligent of, or directly abusing, shared environmental resources. For many corporations, the name of the game is hiring people to lobby state legislators so that environmental regulation never impedes their profits.</p>

<p>Each local area has their own specific environmental concerns, but there are also the global concerns, namely the pollution of the ocean and the carbon emissions in the atmosphere. These are shared concerns that must be addressed, and cannot be addressed with isolated thinking.</p>

<p>We live in an incredible age of abundance where you can order a product from anywhere in the world and have it shipped to your doorstep. A global network of farmers gives you the illusion that crops are in season year-round. Almost anything you can imagine can be manufactured to the exact shape that you envision and mass produced using plastic molds. It is an important question: <em>Can we continue this level of production and efficiency and also be sustainable?</em></p>

<p>I am optimistic that the answer is yes, and that modern society is not incompatible with sustainability. However, much would need to change in order for sustainability to be realized.</p>

<p>It can be hard to grasp how far removed our modern energy consumption is from the span of human history, but it helps to translate the energy that we regularly use and take for granted into manual labor, or the number of slaves needed to generate that energy.</p>

<p>If you convert the amount of energy consumed by a typical individual living in a first world country, the estimate is anywhere from the conservative side of needing 50 slaves to generate the electricity for their residence, to easily over 100 slaves if you include the energy consumed in their transportation, and in growing and transporting the food they eat.</p>

<p><em>Imagine that: Living in modern society, and living a “normal” middle class life, with luxuries like washing machines, personal cars and computers, and not having to grow your own food, is the energy-consumption equivalent to having 50-100 slaves personally working for you.</em></p>

<p>To get an idea for the math behind these estimates:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jancovici.com/en/energy-transition/energy-and-us/how-much-of-a-slave-master-am-i/">How much of a slave master am I?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.tf.uni-kiel.de/matwis/amat/semitech_en/kap_8/basics/b8_1_1.html">Joules, Watts, Kilowatthours</a></li>
</ul>

<p>When I did the math for myself, doing a conservative estimate of just taking into account my monthly electric bill and commute, the number came to 84 slaves.</p>

<p>The conversion of human mechanical power to electrical power is pretty terrible, as demonstrated by <a href="https://youtu.be/3fTVn96gUSQ?t=1898">Walter Lewin in this MIT physics lecture</a>. You can turn the a crank until you’re red in the face, and you would be lucky to have some toasted bread to show for it. It’s something to think about while you blast your AC in summer.</p>

<p>It’s important to note, that the energy efficiency of our most used sources of power—be it burning fossil fuels, nuclear power, and even solar—tends to be pretty terrible and at less that 50%. The other half of potential energy is lost as other means, like heat. Yet, despite these inefficiencies, we continue to use these large amounts of energy to satisfy our standard of modern living to live like kings.</p>

<p>All of this energetic abundance is only made possible by the trees and organic life that lived and died millions of years ago. The fossil fuels that we extract from the Earth is, in simple terms, highly concentrated energy in limited supply.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/07/keywest-frame2.jpg" alt="Key West, FL" /></p>

<p><em>We are facing many environmental challenges, and I am flabbergasted that being concerned about the environment is a political stance.</em> People can devote their lives—decades of hard work—to developing a scientific understanding of the environment, while people with no such training can simply deny their findings and life’s work. If you say the problem doesn’t exist, that doesn’t make it go away.</p>

<p>There is a growing distrust of experts and science in political arenas that is concerning. Skepticism is important, but because of the internet and how easy it is to research, the <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/david_dunning_why_incompetent_people_think_they_re_amazing">Dunning Kruger</a> effect is running rampant. People who read about issues for a few minutes believe that they understand the topic more than people who have been researching it for their whole lives. In this regard, coronavirus may be delivering a dire wake-up call.</p>

<h3 id="connection">Connection</h3>

<p>The Black Lives Matter movement and the environmental challenges we face at first seem like completely separate issues, but they are connected. <em>These issues perpetuate because capable people are inactive and silent. These problems perpetuate because we believe that there is no harm in isolated actions.</em></p>

<p>The message of BLM is that black individuals should be respected and honored; not “accidentally” executed without cause and without even an arrest or trial. When an officer’s negligence results in loss of life, they should face justice.</p>

<p>Similarly, we have been mistreating the environment. The Earth has become our slave. We take what we want, abuse, and don’t show compassion or seek to understand how to be a participant in a healthy and diverse ecosystem. When a corporation’s actions result in lasting damage to the environment, they should face justice.</p>

<p>Not only must we demand more, but we must do more. We need to hold each other accountable and support each other. This is what it means to be a part of a community.</p>

<h3 id="how-to-be-an-active-community-member">How to Be an Active Community Member</h3>

<p>Some of these steps are better taken after the threat of coronavirus has lessened, or done cautiously by wearing a mask and social distancing.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Introduce yourself to your neighbors by bringing them gifts and cards with your contact information on them.</li>
  <li>Clean up litter in your neighborhood.</li>
  <li>Attend local events, such as City Hall meetings, University public lectures, local art gallery events and plays.</li>
  <li>Watch and share documentaries. Or even host a documentary viewing event at your local library or community center. Some good candidates are
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCNXvxXpDJXp-mZu3pFMzYHQ">Our Changing Climate</a> , <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt7763662/">Rotten</a>, and videos about the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GxIDJWCbk6I">Green New Deal</a>.</li>
  <li>Read about issues that are important to you. Some books on the environment that I’ve liked are <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Third-Plate-Field-Notes-Future/dp/0143127152">The Third Plate</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hidden-Life-Trees-Communicate_Discoveries-Secret/dp/1771642483/ref=sr_1_2?dchild=1&amp;keywords=the+hidden+life+of+trees&amp;qid=1593616274&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-2">The Hidden Life of Trees</a>. Also checkout <a href="https://medium.com/@OfcrACab/confessions-of-a-former-bastard-cop-bb14d17bc759">Confessions of a Former Bastard Cop</a>.</li>
  <li>Shop locally at small businesses and farmer’s markets.</li>
  <li>Donate to important causes, community service and outreach programs.</li>
  <li>Support independent journalists.</li>
  <li>Find a local nonprofit and volunteer.</li>
  <li>Become a role model for an at-risk youth through <a href="https://www.bbbs.org/">Big Brothers and Sisters</a>.</li>
  <li>Protest. It is your fundamental human right guaranteed by the U.S. Constitution and the First Amendment.</li>
  <li>Sign petitions, or even create your own petition.</li>
  <li>Post online. Tell your story and share the stories of others.</li>
</ul>

<p>If more people believed that their actions were linked to every other person and living thing on the planet, how would the world change?</p>

<div class="poem">
<p><b>Still I Rise</b></p>

<p>You may write me down in history<br />
With your bitter, twisted lies,<br />
You may trod me in the very dirt<br />
But still, like dust, I’ll rise.</p>

<p>Does my sassiness upset you?<br />
Why are you beset with gloom?<br />
’Cause I walk like I’ve got oil wells<br />
Pumping in my living room.<br />
Just like moons and like suns,<br />
With the certainty of tides,<br />
Just like hopes springing high,<br />
Still I’ll rise.</p>

<p>Did you want to see me broken?<br />
Bowed head and lowered eyes?<br />
Shoulders falling down like teardrops,<br />
Weakened by my soulful cries?</p>

<p>Does my haughtiness offend you?<br />
Don’t you take it awful hard<br />
’Cause I laugh like I’ve got gold mines<br />
Diggin’ in my own backyard.</p>

<p>You may shoot me with your words,<br />
You may cut me with your eyes,<br />
You may kill me with your hatefulness,<br />
But still, like air, I’ll rise.</p>

<p>Does my sexiness upset you?<br />
Does it come as a surprise<br />
That I dance like I’ve got diamonds<br />
At the meeting of my thighs?</p>

<p>Out of the huts of history’s shame<br />
I rise<br />
Up from a past that’s rooted in pain<br />
I rise<br />
I’m a black ocean, leaping and wide,<br />
Welling and swelling I bear in the tide.</p>

<p>Leaving behind nights of terror and fear<br />
I rise<br />
Into a daybreak that’s wondrously clear<br />
I rise<br />
Bringing the gifts that my ancestors gave,<br />
I am the dream and the hope of the slave.<br />
I rise<br />
I rise<br />
I rise.</p>

<p><b>- Maya Angelou</b> <i>(1928-2014)</i></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="sustainability" /><category term="coronavirus," /><category term="covid-19," /><category term="pandemic," /><category term="epidemic," /><category term="sustainability," /><category term="environment," /><category term="reflection," /><category term="black," /><category term="lives," /><category term="matter," /><category term="BLM," /><category term="environment," /><category term="climate," /><category term="change," /><category term="energy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The last few months have highlighted our need for community. Despite the availability of technology and the ability to easily communicate to whomever and whenever we please, we live in an age of loneliness, where many people feel like they have few people (or even no one) that they can rely on for emotional support. Social distancing has been a catalyst of personal growth for many of us as quarantine forced us into solitude and a period of self-reflection. It was the pause button on the busy-ness of everyday life that was uncomfortable, but needed. Empty grocery store shelves broke the illusion of infinite abundance, and alerted us to the fragility of modern society. After only a month of reduced transportation, city air and waterways got noticeably clearer. These experiences seem to say, “You are not in this alone.” Your actions are inexorably linked to every other person and living thing on the planet. In the absence of being able to socialize, I realized how much I took it for granted. I realized all the people I wished I had reached out to and met when I had the chance before my university went online. I also remembered the times in which I was in need of help, desperate for community support but felt so alone. During quarantine, I was learning about lightning and came across the term “Corona Discharge.” It is a luminous effect when an electric field causes charged particles to radiate from a conductive surface. If the electric field grows strong enough, or if the conductive object is brought close enough, this charge can arc between objects, as shown here. Source: TSG MIT Physics The lesson from Corona is clear: If you want community, you have to reach out! Similarly, we need to bridge gaps between perspectives. We are facing many challenges that simply cannot be addressed in isolation. To the contrary, many of our problems arose from isolated thinking—from thinking that the isolated actions of one corporation, or of one person—doesn’t affect others. Now we know better. The two main issues I will touch on are Black Lives Matter and the environment.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Fractals</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/03/interactive-fractals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Fractals" /><published>2020-03-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/03/interactive-fractals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/03/interactive-fractals/"><![CDATA[<iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/TGvKKL2jPwG7jC5m5Z" width="480" height="460" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p><a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/YzPeMGP">Interactive Sierpinski Triangle</a></p>

<p>I am deeply inspired by fractals. They seem to represent the convergence of beauty and logic. In addition to being fun to play with, I love undertaking the challenge of understanding the math that they represent.</p>

<p>I made the following four interactive fractals using JavaScript and HTML5 Canvas, and you can play with them on the code-snippet showcasing website <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott">CodePen</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Click the fractal you want to interact with:</strong></p>

<div class="grid-container">
<div class="grid-item item-1">
    <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/YzPeMGP">
        <img class="no-popup" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/fractals/1.png" />
    </a>
</div>
<div class="grid-item item-2">
    <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/rNaJbyq">
        <img class="no-popup" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/fractals/2.png" />
    </a>
</div>
<div class="grid-item item-3">
    <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/GRgQLMj">
        <img class="no-popup" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/fractals/3.png" />
    </a>
</div>  
<div class="grid-item item-4">
    <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/YzPeMvq">
        <img class="no-popup" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/fractals/4.png" />
    </a>
</div>
</div>

<p><em>The fractal code is based on the tutorials presented by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bIfNwgUVjV8&amp;list=PL7wAPgl1JVvWZPcT0fEfSv5EhLbfWFfVC">Coding Math</a>.</em></p>

<h3 id="math-visualization-resources">Math Visualization Resources</h3>

<p>As I continue to explore math, I notice how I feel lost when I cannot visualize what is happening. However, when there are visualizations available, I find them incredible. The following are resources that I’ve been using as I start my math education journey.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/unit-circle.gif" alt="unit circle animated" />
<!--more--></p>
<h4 id="3blue1brown">3Blue1Brown</h4>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCYO_jab_esuFRV4b17AJtAw">3Blue1Brown’s YouTube channel</a> is full of unique and incredible math visualizations. When I first started watching his videos, I thought that he painstakingly animated all of his content using standard animation software… but I was pleasantly surprised. He programs each of his visualizations using a Python library that he has developed over the years. He scripts each visualization to output to a video file.</p>

<p>His video on divergence and curl is an superb testament to the power of visualization.</p>

<div class="embed-container">
	<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rB83DpBJQsE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h4 id="geogebra">GeoGebra</h4>

<p>Another source of visual math insight is <a href="https://www.geogebra.org/u/amandalynnelliott#favorites">GeoGebra</a> which allows you to visualize various proofs, matrix transformations, or higher math concepts with ease. The community uploads all kinds of teaching aids and resources.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/geogebra.gif" alt="GeoGebra Sine and Cosine Sums" />
<em>Visualization made by <a href="https://www.geogebra.org/m/gNVjYaPy">Tim Brzezinski</a>.</em></p>

<h4 id="desmos">Desmos</h4>

<p><a href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/eg5he4xpg9">Desmos</a> is a deceptively powerful graphing tool that also has fascinating presets for those daring to explore. You can plug in your own equations with variables and enable sliders and animations.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/desmos.gif" alt="Desmos example" />
<em>Play with the <a href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/eg5he4xpg9">Parametric Cycloid</a>.</em></p>

<h4 id="brilliant">Brilliant</h4>

<p>A dedication to making math intuitive is why I have a <a href="https://brilliant.org/courses/">Brilliant</a> subscription. Their courses contain many interactive examples going as high up as Differential Equations and Group Theory.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/brilliant.gif" alt="Brilliant example" />
This polar coordinate flower visualization is a part of <a href="https://brilliant.org/courses/trigonometry/">Brilliant’s Trigonometry course</a>.</p>

<p><em>There is something about dragging a slider that makes things click in my head!</em></p>

<h3 id="beginnings">Beginnings</h3>

<p>I have a giant (and ever growing) list of math visualizations that I want to program. It seemed right to start with the basics: a simple <a href="https://codepen.io/amandalynnelliott/pen/rNaJbPg">2D Cartesian coordinate plane</a>. Here’s a demo of using it to plot vectors that shows the panning and zooming functionality.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/03/vector-math.gif" alt="Cartesian 2D Coordinate Plane" /></p>

<p>More programming math visualizations to come.</p>

<blockquote>Why is geometry often described as “cold” and “dry?” One reason lies in its inability to describe the shape of a cloud, a mountain, a coastline, or a tree. Clouds are not spheres, mountains are not cones, coastlines are not circles, and bark is not smooth, nor does lightning travel in a straight line… Nature exhibits not simply a higher degree but an altogether different level of complexity.<footer>— Benoit Mandelbrot</footer></blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="programming" /><category term="math" /><category term="resources" /><category term="visualization" /><category term="trigonometry" /><category term="calculus" /><category term="fractal" /><category term="interactive" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Interactive Sierpinski Triangle I am deeply inspired by fractals. They seem to represent the convergence of beauty and logic. In addition to being fun to play with, I love undertaking the challenge of understanding the math that they represent. I made the following four interactive fractals using JavaScript and HTML5 Canvas, and you can play with them on the code-snippet showcasing website CodePen. Click the fractal you want to interact with: The fractal code is based on the tutorials presented by Coding Math. Math Visualization Resources As I continue to explore math, I notice how I feel lost when I cannot visualize what is happening. However, when there are visualizations available, I find them incredible. The following are resources that I’ve been using as I start my math education journey.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Semester</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/01/first-semester/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Semester" /><published>2020-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/01/first-semester</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2020/01/first-semester/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve just concluded my first semester at technical university pursuing math and physics undergraduate degrees after a <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/07/finding-purpose/">palm reader</a> suggested this as a potentially more fulfilling career path for me than art.</p>

<p>When I graduated from high school and community college six years ago, I was certain that I would never want to return to academics. However, since starting school, I am pleasantly surprised to discover that I fit in perfectly! I’ve never felt more at ease and confident in my career direction before.</p>

<p><em>Are you as surprised as I am?</em></p>

<p>I enjoy my classes, and often seek additional learning resources outside of class. It feels like a long period of frustration and confusion is finally at a close.</p>

<p>Even still, this was the hardest semester I’ve ever had. The following are two projects that I worked on.</p>
<div id="AKEA"></div>
<h3 id="red-tide-research-project">Red Tide Research Project</h3>

<p style="text-align:center">
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/AKEA-icon-swimming.png" style="width: 250px;" />
</p>

<p>Much of my work this semester went to my technical writing class. The bulk of the class involved group work, organizing 1-3 group meetings a week, all awhile researching an approved topic. Our topic was red tide.</p>

<p>Red tide is a kind of microorganism that proliferates so rapidly that it turns seawaters red. It is a kind of <em>harmful algae bloom</em> that produces dangerous toxins that can affect respiratory and nervous systems.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="red tide" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/AKEA-redtide.jpg" />
    <figcaption>
        Red tide. Source: <a href="https://www.floridadaily.com/southwest-florida-congressmen-want-sba-to-declare-disaster-due-to-toxic-algae-red-tide/">Florida Daily</a>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>When red tide is in bloom, the toxins it creates become airborne via sea spray. If inhaled, these toxins cause respiratory problems. If fish that have been contaminated with red tide are accidentally ingested, these toxins can cause Paralytic Shellfish Posioning, and can be fatal.</p>

<p>Of course, humans aren’t the only animals affected by red tide. It can cause massive fish kills, also kill marine mammals and birds, and can devastate any ecosystem in its wake.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="red tide fish kill" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/fishkill.jpg" />
    <figcaption>
        Brevard County Fish Kill 2012. Source: <a href="https://earthjustice.org/blog/2016-march/the-massive-fish-kill-florida-could-have-prevented">Susan Frazier</a>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>When red tide affects an area, beaches are closed. It disrupts an area’s economy by negatively affecting tourism,  fishing, and recreational industries. Red tide is a complex problem that negatively impacts public health, the ecosystem, and local economies.</p>

<p>My goal with this project as team leader was to <em>create a report that would be useful</em>: something that could even be referenced by people working on addressing red tide. <!--more--></p>

<p>With this goal motivating us, we conducted three interviews.</p>

<p>First we interviewed university biology professor, Jonathan Shenker. During which, we learned that red tide is a naturally occuring phemonenon. The earliest documented sightings date back to the 1500s when Native Americans warned Spanish explores not to eat fish caught in discolored waters…</p>

<p>While red tide is naturally occuring, human activities make it worse. What causes red tide to proliferate out of control is <em>nutrient pollution</em> caused by fertilizer runoff, sewage system leakages, and general poor waste disposal practices. When red tide comes to coastal waters, the presence of these excess nutrients provide the necessary food for the algae to proliferate out of control.</p>

<p><em>Is there any ecological benefit to red tide? Like a forest fire that in the short-term is destructive, but overall is good for the longevity of the forest?</em></p>

<p>Shenker didn’t think so. Red tide appears to have neither a population-controlling benefit, nor any other direct benefit to an affected ecosystem.</p>

<p class="sidenote">As an observation, most harmful microorganisms tend to be abiotic — meaning that they thrive in oxygen-depleted conditions. <br /><br />Harmful algae blooms like red tide thrive in waters deprived of oxygen. Similarly, the kinds of organisms that live in soil and produce toxins also thrive in oygen-deprived conditions: in this case, in compacted soil that lacks air flow. It is these kind of abiotic soil conditions that can lead to agricultural produce recalls. <br /><br />For more on microbiology, I recommend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xzthQyMaQaQ">Dr. Elaine Ingham's lectures.</a></p>

<h4 id="recommendations">Recommendations</h4>

<p>In refraining from too drastic recommendations, like <strong><em>BAN ALL FERTILIZERS</em></strong>, we concluded our research project with the opinion that Brevard County is actually doing a good job in working to address red tide.</p>

<p>I was impressed with the level of research conducted by various programs funded by Brevard County’s half-cent sales tax. The sales tax was enacted by popular vote in 2016, the funds from which go to improving our local bodies of water by means of dredging (a process to remove muck), oyster restoration, and updating old sewage systems. From the first year alone, the sales tax raised almost <em>$94 million dollars</em>.</p>

<p>To gain an understanding of these solutions, we did two more interviews.</p>

<p>First we interviewed Walker Dawson, chief engineer of the one of these programs, the Save Our Indian River Lagoon Project. In talking with him, we learned that from decades of poor waste disposal practices and run off, <em>64,000 acres of Brevard’s Indian River Lagoon sea floor is smothered by muck</em>.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Muck" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/muck.jpg" />
    <figcaption>
        Muck. Source: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HmESfQZ6H3c">Florida Tech Ocean Engineering Students Dredging Project </a>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Is there a thing as too many nutrients?</p>

<p><em>Yes</em>. Caused by excess nutrient buildup, muck effectively smothers the seafloor, causing seagrass dieoffs and preventing sand-dwelling organisms from thriving. When muck is pulled up to the surface, it smells like rotten eggs. Even if you had gills, would you want to call that home…?</p>

<p>The presence of muck has decimated filter feeder organism populations that could filter excess nutrients out of the water naturally. Clams, for instance, are excellent filter filters that live in sand. However, in Brevard, clam populations plummeted in the 90s and since then have never fully recovered.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="What lives in muck" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/Dawson_WhatisMuck.png" />
    <figcaption>
        Nothing can live in muck. Source: Walker Dawson of the <a href="https://www.brevardfl.gov/SaveOurLagoon/Home">Save Our Indian River Lagoon Project</a>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For our last interview, we interviewed Katy Leban of the <a href="https://restoreourshores.org/">Restore Our Shores</a> program, who works to restore populations of filter feeding oysters.</p>

<p>In optimal lab conditions, <em>a single oyster can filter through 50 gallons of water daily</em>. Restore Our Shores has  partnered with local restaurants to donate their used oyster shells. These shells are then used to make oyster cages that become the homes of developing oyster larvae. They also solicit volunteers who live dock-side to hang these oyster cages from their docks and to care for them.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Shuck and Share program" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/oyster_restaurant.jpg" />
    <figcaption>
        Source: Restore Our Shores' <a href="https://restoreourshores.org/shuck-and-share/">Shuck and Share</a> program.
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><em>Our recommendation to address red tide was to continue the two methods that Brevard has already been implementing to positive effect:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Dredging</strong>, or the process of using hydraulic pumps to physically removing the muck that is smothering the estuary seafloor.</li>
  <li><strong>Oyster restoration</strong> so that natural filter feeders may rebound, thus keeping in check the excess nutrients that harmful algae blooms thrive on.</li>
</ul>

<p>From both methods starting to be implemented, people have been reporting improved water clarity in targeted sections of the Indian River Lagoon. For our project, we were impressed with Brevard’s thoroughness in researching red tide and applying these methods that hold promise for rehabilitating the local estuary ecosystem.</p>

<p><em>What you can do to prevent red tide by reducing nutrient pollution:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Don’t use fertilizer</strong>, or know your county’s fertilizer ordinances. For example, in Brevard County there is a ban on Phosophorous fertilizers year-round because the land is already abundant in Phosphorus, while during the rainy summer months, there is a partial ban on Nitrogen fertilizers. Better yet, instead of using fertilizer, study and apply <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xzthQyMaQaQ">microbiology methods</a> which can be more effective in the long-term.</li>
  <li><strong>Don’t wash your car at home</strong>, which can lead to chemical runoff. Instead, go to a car wash, which has to follow thorough waste disposal practices.</li>
  <li><strong>Volunteer at restoration programs</strong> or start an <a href="https://restoreourshores.org/living-shoreline/oyster-mats-gardening/#oystergardeningtab">oyster garden</a> if you live dock-side.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="lessons">Lessons</h4>

<p>While I don’t think we reached our initial goal of <em>making something that other people would use</em>, I would say having this goal motivated us during the project. We learned a lot more than we would have if we were simply trying to complete an assignment. While it would take much longer than a single semester, on the order of years, to research and synthesize new findings that would contribute to this complex topic, our report (at 65 pages) is still a good introduction to red tide.</p>

<p>You can view the table of contents here:</p>

<figure>
<img class="gallery-AKEA" src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/AKEA-gallery/1.PNG" />
<figcaption><a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/contact">Contact me</a> if you would like the full report.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This project has given me an appreciation for how long it takes to contribute research to a field. It’s with good reason that it takes years to do a PhD program. I also got experience and had fun leading the team, delegating tasks, and exploring the topic together.</p>

<p>My leadership style seemed to be effective. I felt like my job as team leader was to ensure that each team member was happy with the delegation of work and felt like their concerns were heard. My style was a combination of applying pressure by holding people accountable to the tasks that they said they would do, while also not taking things too seriously by having fun with the work.</p>

<p><em>It seems like many teams fall apart because of poorly communicated expectations.</em> When a person fails to meet an expectation, resentments can build, and the longer the issue isn’t discussed the more the relationship festers. This was why during the project I would send 1-3 emails to the team per week, clarifying what each member’s expectations were, and answering any questions. We were the only group in the class that didn’t seem to be suffering from interpersonal conflicts.</p>

<p>Also for the class, I designed a logo and icons like we were a bona fide company, and we gave a 20 minute presentation on our work.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/AKEA-presentation.PNG" alt="group presentation" /></p>

<p>When you start a project, <em>embark with the goal of contributing something meaningful</em>, and see what happens.</p>

<h3 id="data-science">Data Science</h3>

<p>This semester I also started working with a group that provides an outlet for me to learn data science and Python. The specific work is analysis of data generated to simulate that of data collected from particle collison events at CERN’s Large Hadron Collider.</p>

<p>Largely, the work is over my head, but I’ve been learning a lot about machine learning techniques like neural networks, regression, and interpolation. I will likely write about these topics in the future once I gain more experience.</p>

<p>Particle physics is one of many fields where we have more data than we know what to do with. <em>Machine learning is just a fancy term for outsourcing the task of data analysis to the computer</em> (or computer clusters if you’re really getting fancy!) These programs can process large datasets faster than any human could.</p>

<p>More to come. In the meantime, I leave you with this snippet of a programming project I did for fun: <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em>. The complex structures it produces are fascinating considering that it is the result of four simple rules and each cell only has two states: alive or dead. You can follow along the tutorial <a href="https://robertheaton.com/2018/07/20/project-2-game-of-life/">here</a>.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2020/01/gameoflife.gif" alt="Conway's Game of Life" />
<figcaption>Project made with Python and PyGame on <a href="https://github.com/amandalynnelliott/Conways-Game-of-Life">GitHub</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="sustainability" /><category term="announcements" /><category term="purpose" /><category term="career" /><category term="work" /><category term="school" /><category term="college" /><category term="university" /><category term="red-tide" /><category term="research" /><category term="leadership" /><category term="programming" /><category term="data-science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve just concluded my first semester at technical university pursuing math and physics undergraduate degrees after a palm reader suggested this as a potentially more fulfilling career path for me than art. When I graduated from high school and community college six years ago, I was certain that I would never want to return to academics. However, since starting school, I am pleasantly surprised to discover that I fit in perfectly! I’ve never felt more at ease and confident in my career direction before. Are you as surprised as I am? I enjoy my classes, and often seek additional learning resources outside of class. It feels like a long period of frustration and confusion is finally at a close. Even still, this was the hardest semester I’ve ever had. The following are two projects that I worked on. Red Tide Research Project Much of my work this semester went to my technical writing class. The bulk of the class involved group work, organizing 1-3 group meetings a week, all awhile researching an approved topic. Our topic was red tide. Red tide is a kind of microorganism that proliferates so rapidly that it turns seawaters red. It is a kind of harmful algae bloom that produces dangerous toxins that can affect respiratory and nervous systems. Red tide. Source: Florida Daily When red tide is in bloom, the toxins it creates become airborne via sea spray. If inhaled, these toxins cause respiratory problems. If fish that have been contaminated with red tide are accidentally ingested, these toxins can cause Paralytic Shellfish Posioning, and can be fatal. Of course, humans aren’t the only animals affected by red tide. It can cause massive fish kills, also kill marine mammals and birds, and can devastate any ecosystem in its wake. Brevard County Fish Kill 2012. Source: Susan Frazier When red tide affects an area, beaches are closed. It disrupts an area’s economy by negatively affecting tourism, fishing, and recreational industries. Red tide is a complex problem that negatively impacts public health, the ecosystem, and local economies. My goal with this project as team leader was to create a report that would be useful: something that could even be referenced by people working on addressing red tide.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding Purpose &amp;amp; Rhythm</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/07/finding-purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding Purpose &amp;amp; Rhythm" /><published>2019-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/07/purpose-rhythm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/07/finding-purpose/"><![CDATA[<p>Depression compelled me to seek help in the form of a retreat. My art career pursuits were leaving me unfulfilled and unmotivated for life, so I brought my sketchbook deep into a Georgian forest in search of clarity and confidence.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/forest.jpg" alt="Visionary Goddess Retreat in Georgia" /></p>

<p>In-between encounters with beautiful people, I heard that the hostel manager was offering palm readings and that she was <em>very good</em>. Having had an experience with a psychic before who was <a href="http://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2017/10/make-the-future/"><em>very bad</em></a>, I decided to give her a shot with an open mind.</p>

<p>Putting my sketchbook in my bag, I went into the reading, her eyes penetrated into mine while she held my hands, measuring lengths of my fingers, feelings the strength and limberness of various features, all while speaking. It was shocking how she <em>knew</em> me, while I had never met her before. I felt so exposed. Some of her statements were so on point, so personal, and I was so in need of hearing them, that at multiple points I almost burst into tears.</p>

<p>While I did not ask her any specific questions, in the middle of the reading, she said I was a creative and artistic person captivated by beauty… but that <em>pursuing an art career would only be a struggle for me</em>. She went on to say that while that was the case, that I had an unconventional mind and actually had a <em>gift for math and physics</em>.</p>

<p>When the reading ended, I wrote what she had said into my sketchbook, and that part stuck in my head like something that didn’t sit well.</p>

<p>“Ugh. Math and physics… <em>Why?</em>”
<!--more--></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/labryinth.jpg" alt="Visionary Goddess Retreat in Georgia" /></p>

<h4 id="years-of-trying">Years of Trying</h4>

<p>Years ago on the cusp of adulthood, I had decided to be artist. It felt like the right thing to do. Making art is fun; why not make a career of it?</p>

<p class="tight"><em>I had tried so many different kinds of creative disciplines:</em></p>
<ul class="tight">
<li>illustration</li>
<li>graphic design</li>
<li>web design</li>
<li>event planning</li>
<li>animation</li>
<li>landscape design</li>
<li>alternative healing</li>
<li>painting</li></ul>

<p>No matter what I tried, I could never seem to summon the motivation to do any discipline on a consistent basis. <em>Once I figured out the fundamentals of how it worked, I’d move on.</em></p>

<p>It seemed like what drives me was <em>not</em> a desire to express the vision of others. I grew bored of marketing once I understood it, and I couldn’t stand being in the position of having a client expecting design work from me and wanting reiterations.</p>

<p>What drives me was <em>not</em> even a desire to express myself artistically. I sat down and painted everyday, but I grew to hate these paintings and had no motivation to finish them.</p>

<p class="tight"><em>I tried enforcing consistency and routine:</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>I tried keeping a record of what I would work on every day — a log of progress with future goals to work towards.</li>
  <li>I tried habit-forming apps.</li>
  <li>I tried the schedule of commiting to just 20 minutes of creativity every day — just long enough to get into the flow state — or short enough to abort and do something else if I just wasn’t feeling it.</li>
</ul>

<p>I was never feeling it.</p>

<p>I read many articles on how to become a professional artist and on how to improve at art. The universal advice in these articles was terrible, always a focus on: <em>“Whatever you do, don’t give up.”</em></p>

<p>Giving up from a place of defeatism, is one thing, but sometimes letting go is exactly what is needed.</p>

<p><em>“Draw everyday”</em> was also terrible advice. Drawing everyday will make you better at drawing, this is true. But it might also make you hate drawing and yourself.</p>

<p>People who like drawing naturally draw almost everyday, and so don’t need that advice. They are probably already professional artists.</p>

<p>People who don’t draw everyday either want to draw everyday but fail to prioritize it, or they don’t want to draw everyday but don’t want to admit it. Most advice targets the first case. <em>The belief here is that the only thing separating a person from a goal is sheer force of will and discipline.</em></p>

<p>The difference here is subtle but very important. Successful professional artists are happy making art everday. Unsuccessful artists are unhappy making art everyday, but hope that one day, when they eventually are rewarded success, they will be happy.</p>

<p>If you are unhappy being an unsuccessful artist, then gaining success won’t make you happy. <em>If anything, success brings obligation and more pressure, things that you will be crushed under if you don’t actually enjoy the work.</em></p>

<p>Looking back at the drawings I made from the retreat, I can feel how they came less from a place of enthusiasm and more from a place of obligation. Feeling like I <em>needed</em> to get better. My sketchbook had become my anchor tethering me to guilt when I would inevitably fail to put any sketches in it. <em>It wasn’t my natural disposition to draw all the time, and no amount of discipline was going to change that.</em></p>

<p>Looking back, the connecting thread that <em>does</em> motivate me, seems to be solving problems, researching, and exploring mysteries. It was this that motivated to try all of these disciplines in the first place, and it’s the very same drive that kept me from being able to commit to any single one of them once I understood them.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/particle-physics.png" alt="particle physics" />
  <figcaption>Source: <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/people/robcolvinart/works/6961167-particle-physics?finish=semi_gloss&amp;p=poster&amp;size=small&amp;gdffi=aa308446f0204ceb814e04f9c214a536&amp;gdfms=84C8A24454FB4F9198F56908E04D71ED">Rob Colvin on RedBubble</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="finding-fun-in-roadblocks">Finding Fun in Roadblocks</h3>

<p>Success isn’t the promise of being happy in the future, but feeling joy in your actions on a daily ongoing basis.</p>

<p>Much of working life involves overcoming roadblocks. It’s only a question of <em>which</em> roadbloacks do you enjoy helping others overcome? People will pay you for helping them overcome roadblocks, and they’ll pay you in proportion to how good you are at it. The more you enjoy it, the better you’ll get at it, the more money you’ll make.</p>

<p>Most people focus on the positives when considering career paths: the fun parts. But I find it much more useful to consider the negatives of a potential career, and ask yourself if you could find joy in that.</p>

<p class="sidenote">
It sounds fun to make games, but could you enjoy spending the bulk of your time debugging code that you've already written?<br /><br />It sounds fun to grow food for your family and town, but could you enjoy spending the bulk of your time doing physical labor, dealing with problems like pests, diseases, and drought?<br /><br />It sounds fun to create recipes for restaurants, but could you enjoy delegating solutions to problems in a high-stress environment, like the kitchen running out of an essential ingredient in the middle of a rush?</p>

<p>All work has positives and negatives. Rather than solely focusing on what work you enjoy, focus on what work you would enjoy for the very reasons that many other people wouldn’t enjoy it.</p>

<p><em>What roadblocks do you enjoy overcoming? What kinds of stress give you a sense of fulfillment?</em></p>

<h3 id="purposeful-process">Purposeful Process</h3>

<p>Despite deciding for art to be my purpose, and trying to adapt myself to it in every way I could think of, at the core of my being, it was wrong for me.</p>

<p>I’m not making the same mistake of declaring a new purpose, because life is not knowing the end. <em>Purpose is not a definition, but a process.</em></p>

<p>You have no purpose alone. Purpose is the process of relating to others and giving to them.</p>

<p>Every person comes here with gifts to be shared, but I’m beginning to think that each person’s gifts may be as unique as their DNA. <em>You will find rhythm in a unique blend of actions and relationships that will refine you over time, as long as you remain open, adaptable, and attuned to your heart.</em></p>

<p>Without definition, without the need for self-validation, what do you want to give?</p>

<h3 id="math-and-beauty">Math and Beauty</h3>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/math-woman.jpg" alt="math as a woman" /></p>

<p>When the psychic suggested that I may have a gift for math, my heart sunk.</p>

<p>Math had always come easy to be growing up, and I exceeded grade-levels, being taught algebra in third grade, but my desire to learn math came to an adrupt halt when I was entered in a math competition at the end of elementary school. My team and I couldn’t solve any of the problems nearly fast enough, and so we ended up just waiting for it to be over. It was humiliating.</p>

<p>I didn’t want to learn math because I grew to see it as most high schoolers do: boring, irrelevant, and needlessly difficult. <em>I wanted to do what others would admire. I wanted to make beautiful things, and math did not seem beautiful at all.</em></p>

<p>Now, the more I explore, the more I see how math does contain beauty… it’s harder to see, but beautiful in it’s symmetry and complexity. Math doesn’t reveal herself to anyone all at once, but only parts of her, and slowly, over time, to those who court her.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/pinterest1.png" alt="pinterest" /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/pinterest3.png" alt="pinterest" /></p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/pinterest4.png" alt="pinterest" />
  <figcaption>You can follow my Pinterest boards <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/amandalynneliot/boards/">here</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="relief">Relief</h3>

<p>I was so locked into tunnel-vision stubbornness that I didn’t want to consider the psychic’s suggestion, but once I did, once I let go of art, I felt liberated. I still draw, but not nearly enough to constitute a full-time job, and I accept that.</p>

<p>Within a month after the retreat, I applied and was accepted to a university, majoring in physics. It was the same university where I applied and was accepted to six years ago before I changed my mind to forgo college to explore vague ideas of <em>making art</em> and <em>starting a business</em>.</p>

<p>I didn’t go to college because <em>I didn’t want to make the mistake of choosing a career that wouldn’t make me happy</em>, but in isolating myself to art, that’s exactly what I was doing: <em>living in present unhappiness for the promise of happiness in the future.</em></p>

<p>At first I felt silly, embarrassed for having made the mistake of not attending the first time… but six years has made me a very different person. I’m not going to university in order to prove something, or to get it over with, but to the contrary: I could not be more excited for the experience, community, and resources.</p>

<p>Tuition being over $40,000 for the year, I somehow managed to qualify for enough scholarships and financial aid that I didn’t need to take out any loans. This change in direction has brought tremendous relief, and everything seems to be falling into place.</p>

<p>In these waning days of summer before I start classes next month, I fill my free time with math, of all things. I put aside my sketchbook in exchange for a notebook and calculator. When people see me doing math, they ask me if it’s homework. It’s like people assume that I couldn’t possibly doing math for fun. ;-)</p>

<p>It is surprising to me still, everyday, that I find math problems so fun. <em>How was that psychic able to see something about myself that I couldn’t?</em></p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/07/mathgirl.jpg" alt="math girl" />
  <figcaption>Source: <a href="https://byronegg.tumblr.com/post/32668902282/delaware-today-this-is-a-piece-for-delaware">Byron Eggenschwiler</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="becoming-nature">Becoming Nature</h3>

<p>Purpose is not a definition, but a feeling, a general direction. <em>It’s important to remain open and unencumbered by your own preconceived notions about who you are and what you’re here to do.</em> I started this year sure of the fact that I was not a mathematically-minded person, that I was not cut out for science fields, and that I didn’t like academia.</p>

<p>In letting go, all these preconceived notions flew out the window.</p>

<p><em>It feels like… becoming nature.</em> The forces of nature around us consistently operate from a place of wisdom despite our ignorance of how these forces scientifically work. I can’t communicate how this works, and many Eastern mystics have attested that such truths are beyond words. But what I can say is that life is better lived in the flow of this force than against it. <em>You always have the choice in action between what is natural and what is unnatural.</em></p>

<p>The distinction of what is natural for me, doesn’t feel like a choice. The only choice is to accept what is and flow with that truth… or not — and accept the consequences either way. It is a choice made in every present moment.</p>

<p>Fear wants you to have a clearly defined destination. Fear wants reassurances, rationalized explanations, proof.</p>

<p>Maybe the only constant is change. Maybe your purpose can’t stand to be caged anymore than you would. Maybe the very narrowing rationalizations that serve to placate our fears simultaneously dampens a spirit that is fearless in it’s expansion.</p>

<p>Becoming nature feels like getting out of my own way.</p>

<p>You want to find your purpose? Stop looking for it. Let it introduce itself to you, let it change you, and let it both confirm and disprove everything you’ve ever thought about yourself.</p>

<p>I’m not trying anymore, and yet making more progress than ever. I’m letting myself be as I am, while accepting that I don’t know what that is. It’s so difficult to accept how easy it is. In moments of blissful clarity, I remember completeness. It’s when I forget that I feel fearful and separate.</p>

<p>What do you do when you feel complete? I’m sure whatever it is, it’s a force of nature to behold.</p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="purpose" /><category term="career" /><category term="work" /><category term="self-love" /><category term="happiness" /><category term="my-story" /><category term="school" /><category term="college" /><category term="university" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="math" /><category term="art" /><category term="physics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Depression compelled me to seek help in the form of a retreat. My art career pursuits were leaving me unfulfilled and unmotivated for life, so I brought my sketchbook deep into a Georgian forest in search of clarity and confidence. In-between encounters with beautiful people, I heard that the hostel manager was offering palm readings and that she was very good. Having had an experience with a psychic before who was very bad, I decided to give her a shot with an open mind. Putting my sketchbook in my bag, I went into the reading, her eyes penetrated into mine while she held my hands, measuring lengths of my fingers, feelings the strength and limberness of various features, all while speaking. It was shocking how she knew me, while I had never met her before. I felt so exposed. Some of her statements were so on point, so personal, and I was so in need of hearing them, that at multiple points I almost burst into tears. While I did not ask her any specific questions, in the middle of the reading, she said I was a creative and artistic person captivated by beauty… but that pursuing an art career would only be a struggle for me. She went on to say that while that was the case, that I had an unconventional mind and actually had a gift for math and physics. When the reading ended, I wrote what she had said into my sketchbook, and that part stuck in my head like something that didn’t sit well. “Ugh. Math and physics… Why?”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Escaping Black Holes</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/04/escaping-black-holes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Escaping Black Holes" /><published>2019-04-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/04/blackholes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2019/04/escaping-black-holes/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>People are born stars, naturally giving off light and warmth. <br />Through negative circumstances, some collapse in on themselves and become black holes.</p>
</blockquote>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/04/blackhole.webp" alt="Gargantua black hole" />
  <figcaption>Source: <a href="https://io9.gizmodo.com/the-truth-behind-interstellars-scientifically-accurate-1686120318">Gizmodo</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>With the recent first ever <a href="https://www.inverse.com/article/54781-what-does-m87-change-what-we-know-about-black-holes-not-much-and-thats-awesome">photograph of a black hole</a>, this is an exciting time to be alive. We are making progress unraveling the mysteries of the creative and destructive forces that make up our universe, and also, our minds.</p>

<p>The story of good versus evil is as old as mankind itself, but instead of “good” versus “bad,” I find it useful to view these as creative and destructive forces. Creation is what we consider good: love, light, the spark that produces things of value, birthing new life and art. Destructive forces we see as the evil antagonist to this: that which ends life, monsters that lurk in the shadows waiting to devour us, our fear of the unknown, psychopaths, and those that harm themselves or others.</p>

<p>For the last year, I’ve had my personal struggles with these destructive forces. I have not been able to create much, but not for lack of trying. I have been riddled with mental traps put in place from years of schooled conditioning… but now I am finally free.</p>

<p>I share my journey with hopes that others may escape the black holes of their darker natures so that they can feed their light of creation.<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="the-light-is-within">The Light is Within</h3>

<p>I open with a poem:</p>

<div class="poem">
<p><b>Anxiety</b></p>

<p>"Am I doing the right things?"<br />
The question claws from within your skull,<br />
Digging for it's answer.<br /></p>

<p>It's a question best left to others,<br />
to the experts:<br />
popes,<br />
professors,<br />
prophets,<br />
politicians,<br />
and the popular,<br />
Who are all more than willing<br />
to put your scarred brain at ease<br />
for a price<br />
you can't afford.</p>

<p>But what of the work that goes unnoticed?<br />
Countless hours of work done for no applause,<br />
done alone,<br />
in faith<br />
that the allusive answer<br />
is within reach</p>

<p>You venture on a ledge,<br />
the breath of the living abyss whirling up and around,<br />
quickly pulling back,<br />
beckoning you to the dark unknown.</p>

<p>Will you jump?<br /><br /></p>


<p>Is the most meaningful work<br />
done in this dark solitude,<br />
when you can't even see<br />
the page?<br /><br /></p>


<p>You make out stars,<br />
pinpricks in the sky<br />
that guide your way.</p>

<p>The gold stars you were so proud to earn as a kid,<br />
cheap beacons shining your way,<br />
directing your path<br />
away from rocky shores.</p>

<p>These symbols of safety<br />
are now neither sticky nor shiny,<br />
with glue pleeing,<br />
They fall.<br />
You hear them hit the ground one at a time with a loud thud,</p>

<p>THUD!</p>

<p>THUD!</p>

<p>THUD!</p>

<p>You turn around,<br />
a lost child,<br />
grasping<br />
for the figure who will illuminate,<br />
who will ignite once more<br />
your fading sky…<br />
You wait and wait.<br />
Aching heart, you wait.<br />
The day having exhausted itself,<br />
you are alone for the cold night.<br />
No one comes to your aid,<br />
and you make camp<br />
amid your aging pile of unfulfilled expectations.</p>

<p>In the name of survival,<br />
you build a fire<br />
and pick each sticker up, one at a time,<br />
Throwing it in<br />
Watching them blaze<br />
Keeping you warm<br />
and for once you know</p>

<p>This is right.</p>
</div>

<p><br /></p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/04/goldstars.webp" alt="falling gold stars" />
  <figcaption>Source: <a href="https://lematworks.tumblr.com/image/166928743457">Lemat Works</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Growing up, I was the “smart” kid. The one with straight-A’s, in gifted programs, and by all accounts, going places. These labels became a part of my identity, and I became so dependent on authority approval and guidance, that it led to my professional <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/04/manipulation/">manipulation</a>.</p>

<p>The school routine hijacked my intrinstic motivations to do work, with extrinsic ones. Rather than doing work because of the fulfillment it gave me, I pursued work based on the opinions of others. Easy enough when you have one authority to please, a single teacher, but upon entering the real world, who is your master?</p>

<p>Rather than love guiding my way, fear led me to dark places. Fear is a compelling reason to get schoolwork done, but let’s be honest, schoolwork isn’t meaningful work. The real world doesn’t value memorization and reguritation of information, the skill that I had largely been trained to do. Once I entered the real world,the only things I produced that people valued were creative works that only poured out of me once I released the resistance and fear getting in my way.</p>

<h3 id="talking-to-yourself">Talking to Yourself</h3>

<p>In the six years since graduating school I have cycled through periods self-hate where I would beat myself up for not being “good enough,” with occasional periods where I finally let go, embrace <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2017/04/365-days-of-self-love/">self-love</a>, and as a result, my creative works would effortlessly flow out of me.</p>

<p>But no matter how many positive affirmations I told myself, the sessions of repeating “I am good enough” in the mirror, the destructive force was always in the background, gaining strength, until it would once again knock me down like a tidal wave.</p>

<p>I was so sick of these thoughts that I just wanted to kill their source, and perhaps that was why they kept coming back. I remembered the lesson that <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/02/mental-illness/">insanity is doing the same things</a> over and over again but expecting different results, so I tried something else. I stopped trying to kill this destructive voice and instead gave it a name: Brutus.</p>

<div class="tenor-gif-embed" data-postid="5636559" data-share-method="host" data-width="100%" data-aspect-ratio="1.0"><a href="https://tenor.com/view/space-weird-alien-portal-worm-hole-gif-5636559">Space Weird GIF</a> from <a href="https://tenor.com/search/space-gifs">Space GIFs</a></div>
<script type="text/javascript" async="" src="https://tenor.com/embed.js"></script>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Brutus, who had been the source of so much pain in my adult life, to my surprise, actually had the purpose of protecting me. This is surprising: What possible benefit could come from being so hard on yourself? But all habits, even the destructive ones, have some kind of positive benefit. Otherwise, we wouldn’t do them.</p>

<p>I let Brutus express his purpose, and I finally understood. He was born as a way for me cope with my anxiety about my place in the world, my fear of abandonment, and as a way to reinstate my “brilliant kid” status. According to Brutus, while I had been “brilliant” in school, in the real world, I no longer was, and regaining this label was the key to my survival.</p>

<p>The only problem? The stress of this would make me so exhausted that my mind would entertain suicidal thoughts as a form of self-relief… because at least when I’m dead I don’t have to struggle to become “brilliant” anymore…</p>

<p>It sounds dark and overdramatic, but these are not the thoughts of my present rational self. Brutus, I discovered, was a fractured past self in need of reintegration.</p>

<p>Later, I realized how I couldn’t have chosen a better name. In ancient Rome, Brutus was one of the leaders of the rebellion that assasinated Julius Caesar. Brutus, in stabbing his friend in the back, thought that he was doing what was the best for Rome, but those actions would lead to it’s undoing. The government was thrusted into a civil war, and the Roman Republic soon was no more.</p>

<p>My own personal Brutus similarly thought that the key to my future survival was in present suffering, but you can’t beat me into the ground and raise me up at the same time. I am relieved to have finally put an end to this civil war within my mind.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/04/deathofcaesar.jpg" alt="Vincenzo Camuccini's depiction of the death of Julius Caesar." />
  <figcaption>Vincenzo Camuccini's depiction of the death of Julius Caesar (1798)</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2019/04/destruction.jpg" alt="Destruction painted by Thomas Cole" />
  <figcaption><i>Destruction</i> painted by Thomas Cole (1836)</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="black-hole-questions">Black Hole Questions</h3>

<p>My negative thoughts centered around not feeling good enough, having disappointed others, and of being a failure. No amount of combating these thoughts with positive affirmations worked. The problem was not in the answers being positive or negative, but the fact that I was asking these questions in the first place.</p>

<p>Questions like:</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>Am I good enough?</em></li>
  <li><em>What do others think of me?</em></li>
  <li><em>Where should my skills and career be at this age? Am I behind?</em></li>
  <li><em>Is my art, my work, good enough?</em></li>
</ul>

<p>The problem with these questions is that their answers are irrelevant. Even if there was an authority on these matters (the notion of such a person sounds ridiculous), so what if they thought that you’re not good enough, your art sucks, and you’re way behind and too old to do your work. You have your answers, now what?</p>

<p>So what if you aren’t good enough. You exist. There is no governing authority determining your worthiness to have life. What do you want to do?</p>

<p>So what if your art isn’t good enough. Do you want to make art anyways?</p>

<p>So what if you’re too old. Do you want to get started anyways?</p>

<p>The answers to these questions, positive or negative, are irrelevant because these are questions that are black holes that will do nothing but suck your energy and give nothing back.</p>

<p>I remember when I was an emo pre-teen, in the throws of angst, I would often ask myself, “<em>What’s the point?</em>” I would ask this to the point of depression. Eventually, I got fed up, and realized that this question amounted to nothing but the desire to self-destruct. It was a black hole that when fed with my attention, would grow in power to the point of threathening my life.</p>

<p>Entertaining these kinds of questions are as toxic as drinking bleach. If you value your life, if you value the creative force in the world, then treat yourself as a ball of energy, radiating light. Your thoughts can either feed or dim your light. The people who resort to destructive actions are those who have collapsed in on themselves, but that doesn’t mean they are lost. Protect your light and the light of others.</p>

<p>If life gets you down, look inward. Find the spark within yourself and know that everything that you want can only be found within. <em>Enjoy</em> your existence, your free will, and do whatever the hell makes you happy.</p>

<p>You are the star guiding your path.</p>

<div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:150%;position:relative;"><iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/l41YiCpYzf1Ju32kU" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p><a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/star-davestrick-l41YiCpYzf1Ju32kU" style="overflow:hidden"></a></p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="self-love" /><category term="happiness" /><category term="trauma" /><category term="healing" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="my-story" /><category term="school" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[People are born stars, naturally giving off light and warmth. Through negative circumstances, some collapse in on themselves and become black holes. Source: Gizmodo With the recent first ever photograph of a black hole, this is an exciting time to be alive. We are making progress unraveling the mysteries of the creative and destructive forces that make up our universe, and also, our minds. The story of good versus evil is as old as mankind itself, but instead of “good” versus “bad,” I find it useful to view these as creative and destructive forces. Creation is what we consider good: love, light, the spark that produces things of value, birthing new life and art. Destructive forces we see as the evil antagonist to this: that which ends life, monsters that lurk in the shadows waiting to devour us, our fear of the unknown, psychopaths, and those that harm themselves or others. For the last year, I’ve had my personal struggles with these destructive forces. I have not been able to create much, but not for lack of trying. I have been riddled with mental traps put in place from years of schooled conditioning… but now I am finally free. I share my journey with hopes that others may escape the black holes of their darker natures so that they can feed their light of creation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Faith and Invention Part 2</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-and-invention-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Faith and Invention Part 2" /><published>2018-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-n-invention2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-and-invention-part-2/"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-and-invention-part-1/">part one</a> I discuss the personal benefits of faith in overcoming challenges life throws at you.</p>

<p>Now in this second and final part, let’s extend that perspective to encompass the world.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/07/BokTower.jpg" alt="Bok Tower" /></p>

<h3 id="faith-is-risky-business">Faith is Risky Business</h3>

<blockquote>
Persons with high levels of personal mastery… cannot afford to choose between reason and intuition, or head or heart, any more than they would choose to work on one leg or see with one eye.
<footer>― Peter Sage</footer></blockquote>

<p>Leaders and inventors don’t only focus on what is commonly accepted. Allergic to conformity, visionaries are strange with their habit of constantly challenging our assumptions. Their resulting insights, though beneficial to society, can be detrimental to those whose empires depend on upholding the status quo.</p>

<p><em>The very act of innovating means to make what existed before obsolete.</em></p>

<p>Innovation is only good for business if <em>you’re</em> the one innovating.</p>

<p>History has not been kind to most visionaries. The more resistant to change we are as a culture, the more they suffer at our hand. They lie in silent anguish, their works a well-kept secret. They are burned at the stake, exiled, or condemned to drink poision―a justly punishment for “poisioning the minds of youth.”</p>

<p>People with faith change things, and change is uncomfortable.</p>

<p>Those with faith are regarded as foolish or are met with concern, and why wouldn’t we be? We are standing on ground that doesn’t exist―yet.<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="dreamers-vs-leaders">Dreamers vs Leaders</h3>

<p>Faith is beyond fantasy.</p>

<p>Faith is what allows you to persevere through failure. Without faith, Thomas Edison would have been a person who dreamed and talked about the concept of a lightbulb, maybe even gotten people excited about it, but he never would’ve gone through the trials to make electric light a reality, and we wouldn’t know his name today.</p>

<p><em>Can you imagine going through a thousand failed experiments without faith?</em></p>

<p>When a person’s inner faith surpasses their fear of being ridiculed enough to inspire them to take action, they become a leader.</p>

<p>Trying to lead from a place devoid of faith, but full of wishful thinking and blind optimism, is exhausting.</p>

<p>Leadership requries a lot of energy, but it’s not accurate to say that this energy is generated purely from within the leader. This energy is given to the leader from those he is in resonance with.</p>

<h3 id="the-true-nature-of-inspiration">The True Nature of Inspiration</h3>

<p>We are all frequency. You resonate strongly with an action only because there are other people who are matching your giving frequency on the receiving side.</p>

<p><em>Inspiration is a telepathic call-to-action.</em></p>

<p>Have you ever followed a content creator, and then saw that they posted something that was so immediately relevant to you at the time, that was the exact guidance you needed for a specific problem? This happens to me and my friends all of the time.</p>

<p>When I follow my inspiration, I resonate more with people. It’s almost like people, consciously are not, are asking for specific things, specific answers or experiences, and that energetic call-to-action then finds the person best able to respond through their work.</p>

<p>Inspiration is an indication of cosmically-supported energy transference.</p>

<p>Faith. Inspiration. Intuition. These are all the same words for the same thing.</p>

<p class="sidenote">
<span style="text-decoration:underline;">vocare (v.) Latin</span> - to answer a call; usually describes life in a religious order but also means to recognize "a voice." This voice is distinct and like no other. It invites you to follow it.
</p>

<p><em>The word vocation literally translates to a calling―something you have been called to do.</em></p>

<p>You can call this voice a number of things. Your higher self, Spirit, Source, Collective Consciousness, God, the Universe…</p>

<h3 id="education-for-inventors">Education for Inventors</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, it’s rare for people to enter adulthood with their connection to their inner voice intact.</p>

<p>The circumstances that brought me to calling the suicide hotline was a life lived ignoring that voice in my head. To understand how that happened, we need to go back to the invention of the light bulb.</p>

<p>The story of Edison’s brilliant invention is incomplete without talking about what technology his lightbulb made obsolete: the kerosene lamp.</p>

<p>Thanks to this new invention, industrial giant John D. Rockefeller was almost put out of business. With time, his ruthlessness brought him back, stronger than ever, but he never forgot the lesson.</p>

<p>Rockefeller was a strong supporter and philanthropist for public education―but only for <em>his</em> kind of education.</p>

<blockquote>I don't want a nation of thinkers. I want a nation of workers.
<footer>― J.D. Rockefeller</footer>
</blockquote>

<p>The purpose of the school system Rockefeller helped build and what we still have today, isn’t to educate, but to homogenize. It isn’t to develop uniqueness, but to get everyone to think the same. What better way to accomplish this than to condition children to conform <em>each other</em>?</p>

<p>School typically is a pleasant experience for children until third grade. Around that time, school stops being fun, and kids start learning to ruthlessly attack any idea―or other kid―that stands out as different.</p>

<p>Classrooms are battlegrounds for young inventors who are condemned to outcasting and remedial classes―too bored to engage, feeling too stupid to do anything meaningful, and labeled a freak.</p>

<p>Growing up at this age was a painful experience for me. I believed I was an introvert, but my social isolation was actually a way for me to protect myself against the ridicule and outcasting that would happen whenever I would express my “strange” ideas.</p>

<p>I find it hard to imagine bullying remaining such a systemic problem without the conforming and comparison machine we call school nurturing such harmful behavior. Bullying is not natural, but it’s just one of many pain inducing things we do when we learn to ignore our inner voice―our collective voice―which are both one in the same.</p>

<p>Is it any wonder why most of the world’s innovators are school dropouts?</p>

<h3 id="time-to-leap">Time to Leap</h3>

<p>There are things in the world that upset me… Our lack of understanding in mental illness and the negative impact we are having on the planet, for starters.</p>

<p>And I am supposed to accept these powerless narratives, roll over and wait for the end?</p>

<p>I don’t think so.</p>

<p>I have faith in the voice in my head leading me to research into alternative perspectives on “<a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/02/mental-illness/">mental illness</a>.” Many people believe that they are victims of genetics and circumstance, that diagnoses are life sentences, and that there is no hope outside of a pill bottle. I reject this.</p>

<p>I also have faith in a future where we live <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/06/sustainability/">sustainably</a> with our environment. Many wish to ignore the detrimental impact that carrying on with “business as usual” is having on our blue planet, and to pretend that that the problem doesn’t exist. My faith gives me the courage to look, but instead of accepting what I see, I’m free to imagine and invent new futures.</p>

<p>I have made peace with my faith and the risk that expressing it requires. The ground I stand on may not exist yet, but I invite you to join me in building it.</p>

<blockquote>You have to leave the city of your comfort and go into the wilderness of your intuition… What you'll discover will be wonderful. What you'll discover is yourself.
<footer>― Alan Alda</footer></blockquote>

<p>No path is better than the one taken on unwavering faith. The gift is not the destination, but the journey. It’s not what comes to be, but what you are <em>becoming</em>.</p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/07/BokTower2.jpg" alt="Bok Tower" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="faith" /><category term="invention" /><category term="intentions" /><category term="mastery" /><category term="leadership" /><category term="inspiration" /><category term="education" /><category term="rockefeller" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In part one I discuss the personal benefits of faith in overcoming challenges life throws at you. Now in this second and final part, let’s extend that perspective to encompass the world. Faith is Risky Business Persons with high levels of personal mastery… cannot afford to choose between reason and intuition, or head or heart, any more than they would choose to work on one leg or see with one eye. ― Peter Sage Leaders and inventors don’t only focus on what is commonly accepted. Allergic to conformity, visionaries are strange with their habit of constantly challenging our assumptions. Their resulting insights, though beneficial to society, can be detrimental to those whose empires depend on upholding the status quo. The very act of innovating means to make what existed before obsolete. Innovation is only good for business if you’re the one innovating. History has not been kind to most visionaries. The more resistant to change we are as a culture, the more they suffer at our hand. They lie in silent anguish, their works a well-kept secret. They are burned at the stake, exiled, or condemned to drink poision―a justly punishment for “poisioning the minds of youth.” People with faith change things, and change is uncomfortable. Those with faith are regarded as foolish or are met with concern, and why wouldn’t we be? We are standing on ground that doesn’t exist―yet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Faith and Invention Part 1</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-and-invention-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Faith and Invention Part 1" /><published>2018-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-n-invention1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/07/faith-and-invention-part-1/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/07/BokTower-distant.jpg" alt="Bok Tower" /></p>

<blockquote>We have to continually be jumping off cliffs and developing our wings on the way down.
<footer>― Kurt Vonnegut</footer></blockquote>

<p>I’m on a massage table in an healing room surrounded by candles, crystals, raddles and feathers, not sure what to expect. A strange tall hermaphadite statue with a penis and breasts looks down at me, as if questioning me: <em>What are you doing here?</em> Before I can answer, the Shaman enters, asks me to relax, places a crystal on my abdomen, and gets to work.</p>

<p>As he waves his hands over me, I’m shocked at the feeling of energy shifting in my body, waves of tingling sensations rise and subside… When he’s done I feel relieved, noticable lighter, as if emotional pain had truly left me…</p>

<p>How did I get here―to the point where I am taking a Shaman healing class, exercising enough of an open mind to blow emotional traumas into crystals and have conversations about chakras and energy fields…?</p>

<p>The simple answer to that question is faith.</p>

<h3 id="faith">Faith</h3>

<blockquote>
Miracles are not contrary to nature, but only contrary to what we know about nature.
<footer>― Saint Augustine</footer>
</blockquote>

<p>Faith used to be a dirty word to me, a word that meant foolishly believing in the unreal.</p>

<p>I considered myself a rational person. I told myself that I must see first, and <em>only then</em> will I believe.<!--more--></p>

<p>Things changed when my family was in crisis. I had no reason to believe that things were going to get better. All of the evidence, the doctors, the accepted facts and statistics, pointed to the contrary: Things, unbearable as they were already, were only going to get worse.</p>

<p>Suicidal thoughts richoetting in my head, I couldn’t continue living without faith. The only way I could pick myself up was to believe that things were going to get better, in spite of evidence. There’s nothing rational about my beliefs, but they make me feel better about living.</p>

<h3 id="secular-depression">Secular Depression</h3>

<blockquote>Using logic all on its own to disect the disparate events of life can sometimes tell you how things have happened and may also provide that might help you in preventing future disasters. But logic can't show you the underlying causal forces, can't reveal the mystery or the magic, and can't answer the question "Why?"
<footer>― Colette Baron Reid</footer></blockquote>

<p>The word for the belief system that I used to have, as many do in our non-religious secular society, is called <strong>logical positivism</strong>. It states that no statements have meaning except those backed by impirical evidence. In other words, until you can show me the numbers, the tests, statistics, and pie charts, we have nothing to discuss.</p>

<p>The founders of logical positivism wanted a society where religion and philosophy was stripped of any power, and where only Science held ultimate truth, the God of a secular world.</p>

<p>For better or for worse, we have this scientifically founded society. The downside of stripping religion and philosophy from our lives―from trying to remove any trace of subjectivity from existence―can be felt in the form of emptiness and depression. Life seems to hold no meaning anymore.</p>

<p>Cutting yourself off from meaning makes it harder to cope with the challenges of the world that happen to you “for no reason.”</p>

<p>There are many grey areas of our existence that science has yet to answer: <em>What happens to us after we die? Why are we here? What is the meaning of life?</em> …And we are supposed to live in this black void of meaninglessness, rejecting any potential answers, as we wait for Science to deliver us?</p>

<p>Not me.</p>

<p class="sidenote">For more on logical positivism, I recommend this well spoken lecture by R.C. Sproul: <a href="https://archive.org/details/TheFailureOfScientificAtheismR.C.SproulPhD">Failures of Scientific Atheism</a>.
</p>

<h3 id="harnessing-imagination">Harnessing Imagination</h3>

<p>The interesting thing that happened for my life, is that the more I let myself embrace that dirty f-word called faith, the more that I imagined my life getting better, the more it actually did.</p>

<blockquote>Imagination is everything. It is the preview of life's coming attractions.
<footer>― Albert Einstein</footer></blockquote>

<p>Faith requires an exercise in imagination. Taking the “leap of faith” can easily become an act of suicide without seeing the ledge on the other side and believing that you can make the jump.</p>

<p>Visualizing your future as a continuation of unpleasant circumstances is to <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2017/10/make-the-future/">deny your free will</a> to direct your life. Visualizing catastrophes is an even worse use of imagination. Is a captain stranded at sea truly a victim of circumstance if he’s been asleep at the helm?</p>

<p>We resist faith because we don’t want to be viewed as irrational, or disappointed if reality falls short of our expectations.</p>

<p>It may be safer to accept what is already accepted than it is to venture on any ledge, but don’t expect that lack of action to result in any positive change.</p>

<h3 id="listening">Listening</h3>

<p>Isn’t it funny how counter-intuitive listening to your intuition actually is?</p>

<p>I had to <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2017/04/365-days-of-self-love/">commit to a year</a> of living by the question of “<em>What would somebody who loved themselves do</em>” before I could listen to my inner guidance as second nature.</p>

<p>Living according to your inner voice is a surprisingly rational way of working smarter, of working less, but with more results.</p>

<p>Any inner conflict within you will drain your energy and make it harder to accomplish anything you set out to do. I can’t rationalize having my intuition at odds with my mind. The only justifications to ignore my intuition comes from <a href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/04/manipulation/">fear</a>, which isn’t a fun way to live.</p>

<h3 id="without-the-shadow-of-doubt">Without the Shadow of Doubt</h3>

<p>Doubt clouds your intentions and dims the light of consciousness. We learn to doubt our inner voice once we are conditioned to prioritize how others perceive us over how we feel.</p>

<ul>
  <li>What would you be doing if you already were “successful?” If you already had all the money and accolades you could ever need?</li>
  <li>What would you be doing if you knew that you were never going to be successful―never to attain significant wealth or achievement? What would you do to occupy your humble existence?</li>
  <li>In considering your answers to these two questions, which answers overlap? What work would you be doing no matter how others perceived you?</li>
</ul>

<p>The answers you receive to these questions hold the key to your authenticity.</p>

<h3 id="live-a-life-of-ease">Live a Life of Ease</h3>

<p>I recently applied the above thinking to my own career trajectory and was surprised by the result. I realized that my desire to produce art and to animate has not been nearly as strong as my desire to research and write―specifically into the topics of <em>emotions and consciousness</em>.</p>

<p>Working on my visual skills and getting clients has felt like an uphill battle for a while. I only recently realized that I would never be happy as a visual “hired gun”―taking art commissions or animation jobs in order to execute somebody else’s message. I’ve recently accepted that I am first and foremost a writer, the one conveying the message. I need the freedom to research and write about whatever Providence guides me to.</p>

<p>It’s taken me a long time to be able to say this, but: I trust the path to unfold before me.</p>

<p>We spend so much energy going against who we naturally are, trying to be something we’re not. Life is so much more rewarding when we live like children, simply by letting go and focusing on what comes easy and naturally to us.</p>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="faith" /><category term="intentions" /><category term="future" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="imagination" /><category term="ease" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have to continually be jumping off cliffs and developing our wings on the way down. ― Kurt Vonnegut I’m on a massage table in an healing room surrounded by candles, crystals, raddles and feathers, not sure what to expect. A strange tall hermaphadite statue with a penis and breasts looks down at me, as if questioning me: What are you doing here? Before I can answer, the Shaman enters, asks me to relax, places a crystal on my abdomen, and gets to work. As he waves his hands over me, I’m shocked at the feeling of energy shifting in my body, waves of tingling sensations rise and subside… When he’s done I feel relieved, noticable lighter, as if emotional pain had truly left me… How did I get here―to the point where I am taking a Shaman healing class, exercising enough of an open mind to blow emotional traumas into crystals and have conversations about chakras and energy fields…? The simple answer to that question is faith. Faith Miracles are not contrary to nature, but only contrary to what we know about nature. ― Saint Augustine Faith used to be a dirty word to me, a word that meant foolishly believing in the unreal. I considered myself a rational person. I told myself that I must see first, and only then will I believe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sustainability</title><link href="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/06/sustainability/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sustainability" /><published>2018-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/06/sustainability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/blog/2018/06/sustainability/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/06/spring-Juniper3.jpg" alt="Florida spring" /></p>

<p>We are at odds with our home. We live in disharmony with Planet Earth. Rather than rehashing doomsday statistics, the pollution, ozone, and animal extinction rates, let’s see how simple mindset shifts can empower us to take positive action.</p>

<p>This post is about hope.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p>The first step is always the hardest. It is believing in new possibilities where before there were none. It is letting go of the overwhelm and powerlessness you may feel as a single human being on a vast planet in need of help.</p>

<p>The first part is accepting that no, you can’t do it all, but that also, your actions matter. Your way of living, of being, of thinking, touches everyone that you come into contact with and spreads. Sustainable change is gradual change, and as you know, this is a post about sustainability.</p>

<p>I invite you to make a difference with me. These changes will not be sudden or overwhelming, but to the contrary, are gradual, and might even be fun.<!--more--></p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="imagine">Imagine</h3>

<p>All innovations live first in the imagination. Once we believe in the new exciting possibility of global sustainable living for all, we now have the fun part of filling in the “How.”</p>

<p>Before we can imagine a sustainable planet, first let’s imagine a sustainable home. How would such a home interact with it’s environment? How would it be powered, heated, and eliminate waste? How would its residents get food?</p>

<p>Then let’s expand from that to a sustainable neighborhood. A sustainable town. What would such a town, made up of sustainable homes, look like?</p>

<p>Now with a sustainable town, let’s expand to a sustainable country. What would visiting a sustainable country be like? How would its citizens live? How would you have to adapt to their ways of living?</p>

<p>Suddenly, with the aid of imagination, tackling these challenges before us transitions from an overwhelming to an exciting endeavour. It becomes a catalyst for bringing together local communities. It awakens the pioneer, the problem solver, within all of us.</p>

<p>Doing the above exercise gave me the three following mindset shifts.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="1-trash-doesnt-exist">1. Trash Doesn’t Exist</h3>

<p>We push our pollution out of sight. Ship it off to other countries, dump it in the ocean, or bury it underground. Out of sight, out of mind.</p>

<p>Similarly, what do so many of us do with our emotional problems? Don’t we also try to bury our negative emotions deep within us, with the hope that we’ll never have to deal with them? Out of sight, out of mind…</p>

<p>But now the pollution is on our shores, in our food, in our lungs. There is no hiding from yourself. What within you are you refusing to acknowledge?</p>

<p>Just as we can’t digest our negative emotions, so too the planet struggles to digest our hidden trash.<br />
Just as we are backlogged with unresolved issues, so too is the planet.</p>

<p>Trash is a foreign concept to Earth. Trash, as a purely human invention, are objects that are permanent but no longer usable. To nature, there is no such thing as trash, as waste, as permanence. Everything is recycled. Everything is used again and again into eternity. Everything is made a new into something else. Nothing is permanent, and change is the only constant. Death and rebirth is the cycle that keeps on spinning.</p>

<p>To regain harmony with the planet, we literally need to “throw away” the concept of trash. ;-)</p>

<h3 id="2-accept-impermanence">2. Accept Impermanence</h3>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/06/StAugustine7.jpg" alt="St. Augustine graveyard" /></p>

<p>We are in denial about the impermanence of physical life. We bury our loved ones in thick, impenetrable, cushion-lined boxes. We fear decomposition. We fear the cyclical nature of life that is death and rebirth, and so do our best to build permanent structures, hell, even permanent one-use disposable plastic cups, so we never have to face our mortality. This fear becomes one of the many things we bury inside and try not to think about.</p>

<p>When an animal dies, it goes back to the Earth. It becomes the food for the decomposers in the soil, which in turn, gives nutrients to nearby plants. Animals eat those plants. Animals eat those animals. In whatever fashion, whenever they die, they go back to the soil, and the cycle continues onward. Nothing is wasted. All life is constantly changing into different forms of life. Nature is the ultimate recycler.</p>

<p>To be alive is to evolve. Resisting change, resisting growth, pushing down your negative emotions, which are your catalysts for change, halts your growth. Doing this causes you to be out of tune with the symphony of life.</p>

<p>Letting your emotions flow, learning from them, changing with them, is how you harmonize with yourself, with others, and with the planet.</p>

<h3 id="3-conquering">3. Conquering</h3>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/06/StAugustine4.jpg" alt="St. Augustine canons" /></p>

<p>If we are to regain harmony with the planet, we must let go of the antiquated “conquer the elements” mindset. We not only live on Earth, we are Earth. We are the elements. The only thing we are conquering is ourselves.</p>

<p>You might also find it useful to personify the planet as Mother Earth, or Gaia. It’s easier to violate an inanimate rock than it is to violate your own mother. I admire the cultures that have managed to live in harmony with their environment because of their reverence for nature. The Native Americans, the Aboriginals of Australia, and countless other indigenous cultures that lived for thousands of years in harmony with their homelands. Meanwhile, modern society has only existed for a couple hundred years, and we’re already in trouble.
I find it amusing that we look down on ancient indigeous societies as “primative,” when in fact, we could stand to learn a lot from them.</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<p>We must transmute our negative emotions. We must heal our traumas. This is the process of exaltation, of integration, of recycling the pain that lies in the wastelands of our souls.</p>

<p>The beautiful thing is that once we see living in harmony with nature as a possibility, life takes on magical qualities. You see the consciousness in all life. You see how we are all connected.</p>

<p>Transmutation was always an act of magic. Couldn’t we all use a little magic in our lives?</p>

<p>As above, so below<br />
As within, so without</p>

<p style="text-align:center">***</p>

<p>In the future I will post more about sustainability as I work towards my long-term goal of growing my own food and building a homestead. But for now, I leave you with these links and a photo from my garden.</p>

<p><em>I’m convinced. This is no sunflower, but a beanstalk!</em></p>

<p><img src="https://amandalynnelliott.github.io/assets/img/2018/06/garden-sunflower.jpg" alt="garden- giant sunflower" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/70219642">Planet Earth series on Netflix</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jefffinley.org/money/">Jeff Finley’s unexpected conversation with Mother Earth</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Amanda Lynn Elliott</name></author><category term="personal-dev" /><category term="sustainability" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="emotions" /><category term="sustainability," /><category term="nature," /><category term="environment," /><category term="pollution," /><category term="recycle," /><category term="homestead," /><category term="earth," /><category term="gaia," /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are at odds with our home. We live in disharmony with Planet Earth. Rather than rehashing doomsday statistics, the pollution, ozone, and animal extinction rates, let’s see how simple mindset shifts can empower us to take positive action. This post is about hope. The first step is always the hardest. It is believing in new possibilities where before there were none. It is letting go of the overwhelm and powerlessness you may feel as a single human being on a vast planet in need of help. The first part is accepting that no, you can’t do it all, but that also, your actions matter. Your way of living, of being, of thinking, touches everyone that you come into contact with and spreads. Sustainable change is gradual change, and as you know, this is a post about sustainability. I invite you to make a difference with me. These changes will not be sudden or overwhelming, but to the contrary, are gradual, and might even be fun.]]></summary></entry></feed>